<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The revvards of vertue a comedie / by J.F., Gent.</title>
            <author>J. F. (John Fountain)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 194 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40043</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1647</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18251</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12110794</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12110794</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54200</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40043)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54200)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 68:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The revvards of vertue a comedie / by J.F., Gent.</title>
                  <author>J. F. (John Fountain)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 88 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ja. Cottrel for Hen. Fletcher ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to John Fountain. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54200:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54200:1"/>
            <p>THE Revvards of Vertue; A COMEDIE.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. F.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Ja. Cottrel,</hi> for <hi>Hen. Fletcher</hi> at the three Gilt Cups in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:54200:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54200:2"/>
            <head>The Perſons.</head>
            <list>
               <item>BASILIUS, <hi>the King.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>THEANDER, <hi>the Prince.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The</hi> PRIST.</item>
               <item>PYRRHUS, <hi>a Lord of the Court, the Kings confident.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>NEANDER, <hi>a vain Lord of high birth.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>ENDYMION, <hi>a Lord of a ſmall fortune.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>GERON, <hi>an old jealous Knight, husband to</hi> PHRONESIA.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The</hi> QUEEN.</item>
               <item>CLEANTHA, <hi>a young Princeſs, Neece to the</hi> QUEEN.</item>
               <item>URANIA, <hi>a young Shepherdeſs waiting on</hi> CLEANTHA.</item>
               <item>EVADNE, <hi>daughter to the</hi> PRIEST, <hi>newly come to the Court.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>PHRONESIA, <hi>an ordinary Court-Madam, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the</hi> QUEEN.</item>
               <item>PARTHENIA, <hi>Mother to</hi> URANIA.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>The Scoene, Arcadia.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <pb facs="tcp:54200:3"/>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:54200:3"/>
               <head>Actus 1. Scoena 1.</head>
               <stage>Enter Pyrrhus, Neander, and Endymion.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>BElieve't, my Lords, they ſay the Prince doth wonders.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <l>They ſay he kils a world of men indeed.</l>
                  <l>But 'faith, I think the wonder'd greater been,</l>
                  <l>Had he made but half ſo many live.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>Perchance my Lord, you'd have him turn Phyſitian.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nean.</speaker>
                  <l>Rather then Butcher; 'tis the nobler Trade.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>Why? but they are his enemies he kills,</l>
                  <l>Men that offend, and do deſerve to die.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh! then I think you'll praiſe the Hang-man next;</l>
                  <l>You give a definition of his Trade.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>If I do not miſtake your humour Sir,</l>
                  <l>You never were much taken with this dying:</l>
                  <l>It is a thing (I do confeſs) doth mar</l>
                  <l>A Courtier much.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <l>Why faith my Lord 'tis true.</l>
                  <l>Let broken Merchants and the buſie rout</l>
                  <l>Who durt the Streets, when their deſigns miſcarry,</l>
                  <l>Cry that there's nothing certain in this world;</l>
                  <l>I think there's leſs in that which is to come.</l>
                  <l>Here I am ſure of ſomething: I'm a Lord,</l>
                  <l>And live with Men. But to be turn'd a grazing</l>
                  <l>In the <hi>Elyſian-Fields</hi> that men do talk of,</l>
                  <l>Among Philoſophers ne'er could make a leg,</l>
                  <l>Who purblind grew with viewing of thoſe Stars</l>
                  <l>Ne'er made them worth a groat; and took ſtrange pains</l>
                  <l>In meaſuring Sea and Land, when they'd more need</l>
                  <l>To have a Taylor come and meaſure them;</l>
                  <l>In troth my Lord, here's bleſſed Companie;</l>
                  <l>Who would not change this world for ſuch a life?</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:54200:4"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>Fie, fie, <hi>Neander.</hi> This is too prophane,</l>
                  <l>And relliſheth far more of beaſt then man.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, I ask you pardon: I'd forgot</l>
                  <l>You are a <hi>Vertioſi</hi>—'Tis my Lord <hi>Pyrrhus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That makes me wander from my argument,</l>
                  <l>By putting me in mind o'th' world to come:</l>
                  <l>(A Theam indeed, on which few men ſpeak ſence)—</l>
                  <l>But to the matter firſt propos'd,—My Lord,</l>
                  <l>The thing I only ſtuck at, was that you</l>
                  <l>(So wiſe a man) ſhould give ſo mighty Names</l>
                  <l>To killing Men. Why! celebrate the Plague;</l>
                  <l>What General ever did deſtroy like that?</l>
                  <l>Or ſtudy glorious: Titles for old-age,</l>
                  <l>That kills all thoſe, whom nothing elſe can kill.</l>
                  <l>Great Warriors are but the journey-men</l>
                  <l>Of fatal <hi>Atropos,</hi> whoſe ſwords ſhe uſeth</l>
                  <l>To cut mens lives off, but to ſave her ſheers,</l>
                  <l>Which elſe had ſure been edgeleſs long ago</l>
                  <l>With too much work; and we (for ought I ſee)</l>
                  <l>By this time might have all immortal been,</l>
                  <l>Having by long dying worn out Death it ſelf.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>[Endymion ſmiles]</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, 'faith he that dares diſpute with you,</l>
                  <l>Muſt be a cunning Sophiſter, I ſee;</l>
                  <l>Muſt be content to give you victory,</l>
                  <l>Without receiving truth in exchange for't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <p>The truth is, my Lords, in ſhort, you have all the wit, though I have all the talk — Fare you well; I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve I ſhall not much mar your diſcourſe by my abſence, nor will you much mend my manners by your preſence: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieu.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>[Exit Neand.]</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis a mad Lord as e'er was born: 'twere pretty</l>
                  <l>(If poſſible) to ſit within his skull,</l>
                  <l>And take a Proſpect of his giddy thoughts,</l>
                  <l>Which do like Centaurs ſeem, half Man, half Beaſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>He's too prophane; and chuſeth to buy wit</l>
                  <l>At the expence of Friends, Religion,</l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:54200:4"/>
                  <l>And all, but Ladies ſmiles; which he more values,</l>
                  <l>Then honeſt Men do the kinde looks of Heaven.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>And nothing hates like Reputation won</l>
                  <l>By Arms. He hates all Deities, for <hi>Mars</hi> his ſake<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>And ſwears that Generals onely famous grow</l>
                  <l>By valiant Friends, or cowardly Enemies;</l>
                  <l>Or (what is worſe) by ſome mean piece of chance.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>The truth's, my Lord, 'tis pretty to obſerve</l>
                  <l>How little Princes and great Generals</l>
                  <l>Contribute oft-times, to the fame they win.</l>
                  <l>How often hath't been found, that nobleſt mindes</l>
                  <l>With too ſhort arms have fought with fatal Stars?</l>
                  <l>And have endeavoured with their deareſt blood</l>
                  <l>To mollifie thoſe Diamonds where dwell</l>
                  <l>The fate of Kingdoms; and at laſt have fallen</l>
                  <l>By vulgar hands; unable now to do</l>
                  <l>More for their cauſe then dy; and have been loſt</l>
                  <l>Among the ſacrifies of their own ſwords,</l>
                  <l>No more remembred then poor Villagers</l>
                  <l>Whoſe aſhes ſleep beneath the common flowers</l>
                  <l>That every meadow wears: whilſt other men</l>
                  <l>With trembling hands have caught a victory,</l>
                  <l>And on pale fore-heads worn triumphant bayes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>Believe't, 'tis true.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>Beſides, my Lord, I've thought,</l>
                  <l>A thouſand times; in times of War, when we</l>
                  <l>Lift up our hands to Heaven for victory;</l>
                  <l>Suppoſe ſome Virgin Shepherdeſs, whoſe ſoul</l>
                  <l>'S as chaſt, and clean, as the cold ſpring where ſhe</l>
                  <l>Quench's all her thirſts, being told of enemies</l>
                  <l>That ſeek to fright the long-enjoyed Peace</l>
                  <l>Of our <hi>Arcadia</hi> hence with ſound of Drums;</l>
                  <l>And with Horſe, Trumpets, Warlike Ayrs, to drown</l>
                  <l>The harmleſs Muſick of her Oaten Reedes;</l>
                  <l>Should in the paſſion of her troubled ſpright</l>
                  <l>Repair to ſome ſmall Fane (ſuch as the Gods</l>
                  <l>Hear poor folks from) and there on humble knees</l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:54200:5"/>
                  <l>Lift up her trembling hands to holy <hi>Pan,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And beg his helps: it's poſſible to think</l>
                  <l>That Heaven, which counts the pureſt vows moſt rich,</l>
                  <l>May not permit her ſtill to weep in vain,</l>
                  <l>But grant her wiſh, (for would the Gods ne'er hear</l>
                  <l>The pray'rs of poor folks, they'd ne'er bid them pray)</l>
                  <l>And ſo, in the next Action happeneth out,</l>
                  <l>(The Gods ſtill uſing means) the enemy</l>
                  <l>May be defeated. The glory of all this</l>
                  <l>Is attributed to the General,</l>
                  <l>And none but he's ſpoke loud of for the Act,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt ſhe from whoſe ſo unaffected tears</l>
                  <l>His Lawrel ſprung, for ever dwells unknown.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Lordſhip doth not doubt the Prince his merit.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>By no means, Sir; I know the Prince a man</l>
                  <l>Who owns a ſoul of that vaſt magnitude,</l>
                  <l>That fleſh did never circumſcribe a greater:</l>
                  <l>And merits ſo much from the vertuous world,</l>
                  <l>By's rare example, that the world it ſelf</l>
                  <l>VVere but too mean a preſent to require him.</l>
                  <l>All that I ſay, is what I've thought upon</l>
                  <l>Some hours of ſweet retirement, when I've ſat</l>
                  <l>And view'd the fleeting ſtate of poor man-kind,</l>
                  <l>A thing too giddy to be underſtood.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>Indeed the Prince doth more then give us hopes</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Arcadia</hi> ſhall command thoſe Provinces</l>
                  <l>VVho lately thought our long and happy Peace</l>
                  <l>Had ſoft'ned ſo our mindes, that now we were</l>
                  <l>Fit to be lorded over by their wills.</l>
                  <l>But ſtrange it is to ſee the King ſo little</l>
                  <l>Joy'd with the news, that ſtill he wears a face</l>
                  <l>More troubled then <hi>Cicilian</hi> Seas in ſtorms:</l>
                  <l>And all but for the love of that poor Maid</l>
                  <l>The Prince not ten months ſince took from a Cottage</l>
                  <l>As he a hunting was, and gave the fair</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cleantha</hi> for a preſent.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>Who! <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes.—But ſtay; I ſee him coming
<stage>Enter King.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:54200:5"/>
                  <l>Let us retire. It may be we ſhall hear</l>
                  <l>Some of the thoughts that trouble him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>Huſht.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King</speaker>
                  <l>—Ah! VVhere will this tyrant end? Heav'n! ſhall I ſtill</l>
                  <l>Be Prieſt, and Sacrifice, and Altar too,</l>
                  <l>Unto a paſſion I can ſatisfie,</l>
                  <l>But never conquer? what poor things are Kings!</l>
                  <l>What poorer things are Nations to obey</l>
                  <l>Him whom a petty Paſſion doth command?</l>
                  <l>Fate, why was man made ſo ridiculous? —</l>
                  <l>But I can quench my Flame. And where my prayers</l>
                  <l>Have not prevail'd, my power can command.</l>
                  <l>Who in <hi>Arcadia</hi> dare reſiſt my will?—</l>
                  <l>— But, ſtay! — When this poor Maid, ſprung from a ſtock</l>
                  <l>Low as the Cottage where ſhe firſt ſaw light,</l>
                  <l>Shall call on Vertue, and the Gods to keep</l>
                  <l>Her body (they too weakly have expos'd)</l>
                  <l>White as her ſoul, which all the world cann't ſully;</l>
                  <l>Shall I (whom men call ſacred, and divine,</l>
                  <l>And look on as deriv'd from Anceſtors</l>
                  <l>VVho have not Tombs but Altars) without ſhame,</l>
                  <l>And thouſand bluſhes, dare with ruder force</l>
                  <l>To drive poor Vertue from her cleaneſt Temple,</l>
                  <l>And uſe that power the Gods have given me</l>
                  <l>O'er others, but t'offend them how I pleaſe?</l>
                  <l>By Heaven, by Heaven, I will not.—But I dy.</l>
                  <l>Oh I am mortal. Men but flatter me.</l>
                  <l>Oh fate, why were not Kings made more then Men?</l>
                  <l>Or why will people have us to be more?</l>
                  <l>Alas! we govern others, but our ſelves</l>
                  <l>VVe cannot rule; as our eyes that do ſee</l>
                  <l>All other things, but cannot ſee themſelves.</l>
                  <l>I muſt ſubmit.—I am a King, but LOVE</l>
                  <l>'S a Deity—I am reſolv'd to trie</l>
                  <l>Whether <hi>Urania</hi> will Love, or die.</l>
                  <l>I'll in, and faithful <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> ſtreight ſhall prove</l>
                  <l>My fate. Lords muſt be Pimps, when Kings do love.
<stage>Exit King</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:54200:6"/>
               <stage>[Pyrrhus and Endymion appeare again.]</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>He's gone.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>But he firſt thought on your employment.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>Truth, I have had already but too much on't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>Have you then been the <hi>Mercury</hi> between</l>
                  <l>Him and the fair <hi>Urania?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, I have</l>
                  <l>Already done what Language and Rewards</l>
                  <l>Have power to do. But ſhe's as deaf to this</l>
                  <l>As blind to thoſe. She ſeemeth not to ſee</l>
                  <l>Ought ſhine but Vertue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>But, what can ſhe ſay.</l>
                  <l>Poor Country Girl? VVhere can ſhe find words</l>
                  <l>And reſolution when you do aſſault her?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>VVhy 'faith my Lord, I'll tell you. VVhen I firſt</l>
                  <l>Mention'd the buſineſs to her all alone,</l>
                  <l>Poor ſoul ſhe bluſh'd, as if already ſhe</l>
                  <l>Had done ſome harm, by hearing of me ſpeak;</l>
                  <l>VVhilſt from her pretty eyes two Fountains run</l>
                  <l>So true, ſo native, down her faireſt Cheeks,</l>
                  <l>As if ſhe thought her ſelf oblig'd to cry,</l>
                  <l>'Cauſe all the world was not ſo good as ſhe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  <l>Heaven! how doth this carriage pleaſe me!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>For my own part, I know not what to ſay,</l>
                  <l>Her tears ſo innocently beg'd my pity,</l>
                  <l>That I was ſtraight turn'd over to her ſide;</l>
                  <l>And had forgot the cauſe for which I ſtrove,</l>
                  <l>'Till rallying once again, I once more gave</l>
                  <l>A new aſſault, and urg'd her to an anſwer.</l>
                  <l>All her reply was, No; then humbly pray'd me</l>
                  <l>Not to be cruel to a poor weak maid</l>
                  <l>VVho had not any thing in all the world</l>
                  <l>To give her credit, but her innocence.</l>
                  <l>VVith ſuch ſucceſs as this I often have</l>
                  <l>Aſſail'd her vertue, adding promiſes</l>
                  <l>Of all things I could ſuppoſe might tempt her;</l>
                  <l>But all in vain. This Ermyne will not be</l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:54200:6"/>
                  <l>Perſwaded from the whiteneſs ſhe ſo loves.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>And do you think the King will now uſe force?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>You heard him what he ſaid. I cannot tell.</l>
                  <l>'Tis hard to ſay what men whom reaſon guides</l>
                  <l>Intend to do, much more whom paſſion rides.—</l>
                  <l>But let's away: I would not have him know</l>
                  <l>VVe were ſo neer the venting of his thoughts.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>There comes my Lord <hi>Leander,</hi> let's away.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt ſeverally.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Neander, Cleantha, and Urania waiting on her.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <l>How doth this hour tranſport my ſoul with Joy,</l>
                  <l>To have the bleſſed priviledge to be</l>
                  <l>With fair <hi>Cleantha</hi> — the beſt Princeſs.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleanth.</speaker>
                  <l>I'm glad it makes ſome body happy Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <l>With her who hath my heart—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleanth.</speaker>
                  <p>Have it I, Sir? Pray my Lord then take it again, for I would not be troubled with the keeping ſuch a bauble for all the world.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <l>She, whom great Nature, now grown wanton, made</l>
                  <l>To look upon and ſcorn her other works.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleanth.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, I ſee you are reſolv'd not to ſtudie to no purpoſe. You will have our your Complement, let me ſay what I pleaſe. But, by the by, I hope you will not be angry if I prove ſomewhat like my ſcornful Mother (as you ſay) and make you the firſt example of it. Fare you well.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neanth.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, Madam; I beſeech your Highneſs —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleand.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, my Lord, now I have put you out of your Complement, I'll tarry a little longer.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, You are cruel. How do you kill—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleanth.</speaker>
                  <p>Kill, <hi>Neander?</hi> No ſure, for then you would be affraid to come neer me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <l>Great Princeſs, You are cruel. But I ne'er</l>
                  <l>Could fear Death from ſo fair a hand as yours.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleanth.</speaker>
                  <p>Perchance you do your ſelf the juſtice to think that ſuch will not foul their fingers about you. I beleeve,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54200:7"/>indeed, my Lord, You fear Death leaſt from the hands of a woman, which is the reaſon you chuſe to tarry here at Court among the Ladies, rather then go to the War with the Prince.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, You Ladies have a Priviledge.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleanth.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, my Lord, it's ſometimes a Priviledge to ſpeak Truth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <l>'Faith Madam, You may ſay what you pleaſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleanth.</speaker>
                  <p>Pardon me, my Lord; it would pleaſe me much better if I could ſay you were in the war in <hi>Theſſalia.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <p>Why truly Madam, I could give your Highneſs very good reaſons why I went not to the war with the Prince.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleanth.</speaker>
                  <p>I believe you can, my Lord: and ſo can every body elſe that knows your Lordſhip. It was becauſe you were affraid.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <p>Do not diſgrace me ſo, Madam, I beſeechy you. It was for very different reaſons.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleanth.</speaker>
                  <p>Truely my Lord, You will give very much ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the world, if you ſay what they are; and very much undeceive them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <p>Why then, Madam, to tell you truly, I am ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what troubled with Corns, ſo that I cannot without pain wear a riding Boot: And then I am ſtrangely ſubject to the Tooth-ake, which makes me very unfit to lie in the Field. Which, indeed, were the two main reaſons made me to refuſe the war.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleanth.</speaker>
                  <p>What pity it is ſo brave a minde ſhould be thus unluckily hindred from ſhewing it ſelf!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, I perceive you jeer me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleanth.</speaker>
                  <p>What a quick apprehenſion you have, my Lord! And do not you perceive you merit it?—But the Queen will expect me, and poſſibly Sir, you are by this time ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſatisfied with my company: adieu.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt Cleanth. and Urania.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <p>Pox take her for me, for all ſhe is ſo great a Lady. But what an aſs was I to be ſo out of countenance? Well, 'faith,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:54200:7"/>I even ſee I muſt go and be drunk, to recover my ſelf again: for at the preſent, by <hi>Jove,</hi> I am damnably cow'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit. Neand.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Endymion ſol.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>Alaſs my poor <hi>Urania!</hi> how doth</l>
                  <l>Thy harder fortune vindicate my choyce?</l>
                  <l>Who now dare ſay <hi>Endymion</hi> lov'd too low</l>
                  <l>When he lov'd her that can make Princes die?</l>
                  <l>No more, no more, we muſt ſcorn Cottages;</l>
                  <l>Theſe are the Rocks from whence our Jewels come.</l>
                  <l>Gold breeds in barren Hills, the brighteſt Stars</l>
                  <l>Shine ore the poorer Regions of the North.</l>
                  <l>But, ſay my dear! why didſt thou caſt away</l>
                  <l>Thy Beams, to thaw that Ice, which but makes clouds</l>
                  <l>To ſully thy own face? Unwiſe <hi>Urania,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Let me a little chide thee now.— But Fool;</l>
                  <l>Can <hi>Urania</hi> chuſe but to be fair?</l>
                  <l>Can ſhe help it that ſhe'th pretty eyes?</l>
                  <l>Or gather the ſoft Roſes from her cheeks?</l>
                  <l>Is't in her power to make her lips leſs coral,</l>
                  <l>Her Teeth leſs Pearls? Or will her breaſts obey her</l>
                  <l>If ſhe god bid them to be ſnow no more?</l>
                  <l>No, poor <hi>Urania;</hi> come, we'll both chide Nature;</l>
                  <l>'Twas ſhe, 'twas ſhe alone dealt hardly with thee,</l>
                  <l>When ſhe made thee fairer then all others.</l>
                  <l>Or elſe 'twas Fortune, when ſhe took thee from</l>
                  <l>The freſh delights of thy ſtill Hermitage.</l>
                  <l>There had'ſt thou liv'd, and by ſome ſilver Brook</l>
                  <l>Unenvied ſang away thy ſofter hours,</l>
                  <l>And kill'd a thouſand Shepherds with thy eyes;</l>
                  <l>There hadſt thou gather'd Jewels from the Fields</l>
                  <l>To deck thee with, more beautious then thy Pearls,</l>
                  <l>And like a Queen hadſt chang'd them every day:</l>
                  <l>There hadſt thou never wept, but for the fate</l>
                  <l>Of ſome poor Lamb perchance, which us'd to lay</l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:54200:8"/>
                  <l>Her ſleepy head upon thy lap; No Kings</l>
                  <l>Had threatned thee for being vertuous,</l>
                  <l>Nor Ladies envi'd thee for being fair.</l>
                  <l>Perfections then had been no ſins; but had</l>
                  <l>Receiv'd the little Tributes which kinde nature</l>
                  <l>Gives to thoſe honeſt folks who dwell with her.</l>
                  <l>And had ſhe been <hi>content,</hi> ſhe had been <hi>rich.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And folks thus rich can never be made poor, —</l>
                  <l>But ſtay — I hear ſome coming: I'll away,</l>
                  <l>And ſearch her out: may be ſhe needs my help.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit. Endym.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Queen and Phroneſia.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                  <p>And is the old Knight ſo jealous, <hi>Phroneſia?</hi> It may be you give him cauſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phron.</speaker>
                  <p>No other cauſe an't pleaſe your Majeſty, but that I am with child.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                  <p>He knew not that (you ſay) untill this morning.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phron.</speaker>
                  <p>He knew not certain Madam, till this morning. But he hath more then doubted me theſe fourteen days.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                  <p>Why did he marry, if he thought he could not get thee with child?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phroneſ.</speaker>
                  <p>I cannot tell, an't pleaſe your Majeſty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                  <p>Why doſt not ask him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phron.</speaker>
                  <p>I have.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                  <p>And what ſaith he?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phron.</speaker>
                  <p>He told me —</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                  <p>What did he tell thee?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phron.</speaker>
                  <p>An't pleaſe your Majeſty, you cann't imagine his wicked intentions.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                  <p>What did he tell thee?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phron.</speaker>
                  <p>He told me he marryed only to keep me honeſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                  <p>But now it ſeems he is convinc'd, 'tis more then he can do.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phroneſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Every man beſt knows his own abilities.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, <hi>Phroneſia,</hi> I muſt talk with you a little more.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:54200:8"/>But this place is not altogether ſo convenient for it. Follow me</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt Queen and Phroneſ.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Prieſt and Evadne.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prieſt</speaker>
                  <l>Well now, <hi>Evadne,</hi> my deat child, thou art</l>
                  <l>Come forth upon the Worlds great Stage; and it</l>
                  <l>Muſt be my care, firſt to adviſe thee, then</l>
                  <l>To pray for thee. And this is all that's in</l>
                  <l>My power to do. The reſt muſt be the Gods</l>
                  <l>And thy part to perform. Yet thou'rt innocent,</l>
                  <l>(Oh mayſt thou ſtill be ſo, my childe!) yet know'ſt not</l>
                  <l>Ought but the holy practices of cells,</l>
                  <l>Where vertuous Matrons have inſtructed thee.</l>
                  <l>But now the Scene is chang'd: the Queens commands</l>
                  <l>Have brought thee to the Court, to wait on her.</l>
                  <l>Th'imployment truely Noble; and thou haſt</l>
                  <l>In her the brighteſt Pattern of true Vertue</l>
                  <l>That all the world can boaſt of. But thou'lt finde</l>
                  <l>Few more beſides, whoſe wandering paths are ſafe.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe of thy Sex, thou'lt find ſo ſtrangely vain,</l>
                  <l>That they can think they 've curl'd, and patch'd, and waſh'd</l>
                  <l>Themſelves even into little Deities.</l>
                  <l>They do believe that wanton men ſpeak truth,</l>
                  <l>When to conſume thoſe hours they care not for,</l>
                  <l>They tell them that their eyes are more then Stars,</l>
                  <l>Their cheeks more roſie then the mornings face,</l>
                  <l>And coral learnt its redneſs from the lips.</l>
                  <l>And by degrees they do ſo ſtrangely cheat</l>
                  <l>Themſelves (poor ſouls) into the fond belief</l>
                  <l>That they not only are the faireſt, but</l>
                  <l>The wiſeſt too; and will not be content</l>
                  <l>With all the beauty, without all the wit.</l>
                  <l>And now they are attain'd to that degree,</l>
                  <l>All muſt admire, but none muſt merit them;</l>
                  <l>Until that Time (too old to complement)</l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:54200:9"/>
                  <l>Takes from them all thoſe little Ornaments</l>
                  <l>Which wanton Nature had adorn'd them with</l>
                  <l>And then they do awake, the Dream is done,</l>
                  <l>The Market fall's, and ſome diſtreſſed Knight</l>
                  <l>Unenvi'd bears away what all had courted.</l>
                  <l>This is the common Fate of your poor Sex,</l>
                  <l>(To paſs by what is worſe, yet but too common)</l>
                  <l>When they get great opinions of themſelves.</l>
                  <l>Therefore <hi>Evadne,</hi> let me pray thee ſtill</l>
                  <l>Keep thy beſt Jewel, thy humility.</l>
                  <l>For ſince thou ne'er wilt be more innocent</l>
                  <l>Then now thou art, thou ne'er wilt have more reaſon</l>
                  <l>To think well of the ſelf then thou haſt now.</l>
                  <l>If thou wear'ſt better cloaths; alas, conſider,</l>
                  <l>Each little little Flower that doth in Meadows grow</l>
                  <l>Is better clad then thee, yet is not proud.</l>
                  <l>Hence mayſt thou ſhun that common vice of Courts,</l>
                  <l>Scorn and contempt of others, which oft' have</l>
                  <l>A nobler Vertue, though a meaner fortune.</l>
                  <l>For know, <hi>Evadne,</hi> that this lower world</l>
                  <l>In which we dwell, is not diſtributed</l>
                  <l>According to folks merits: the Gods preſerve</l>
                  <l>That juſtice for thoſe nobler Regions which</l>
                  <l>Themſelves inhabit. Here the mighty are</l>
                  <l>Like mighty Mountains, high, but ſeldom fertile;</l>
                  <l>The richeſt ſoyl is in low Valleys found.</l>
                  <l>Devotion oft-times weeps in humble cells,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt under gilded roofs profaneſs ſings.</l>
                  <l>This is this the world, <hi>Evadne.</hi> — But to come</l>
                  <l>To what I've elſe to ſay, Thy next temptation</l>
                  <l>Will be to love (for hardly 'twixt thoſe Ills</l>
                  <l>Of eaſie love and ſcorn, do Maidens well</l>
                  <l>Direct their courſe) know, thou wilt ſurely have<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Enough to court thee; ſome cauſe 'tis the mode;</l>
                  <l>Others becauſe they 've nothing elſe to ſay;</l>
                  <l>And wiſer folks, becauſe they think me rich.</l>
                  <l>But know, <hi>Evadne,</hi> that to marry, is,</l>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:54200:9"/>
                  <l>The greateſt action of our lives, and merits</l>
                  <l>The greateſt of our cares; and therefore if</l>
                  <l>Thou think'ſt me wiſer then thy ſelf, commit</l>
                  <l>This to my breaſt. But above all, I warn thee</l>
                  <l>Againſt <hi>Neander:</hi> Though thou ſee'ſt him rich</l>
                  <l>In cloathes, as if he would authorize vice,</l>
                  <l>Ye he's a vain, profane, and idle perſon;</l>
                  <l>One that would make me hate the name of father,</l>
                  <l>Should he but call me ſo. — But who's that yonder?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Evad.</speaker>
                  <p>I think Sir his name is <hi>Geron.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prieſt.</speaker>
                  <p>It is ſo. An impertiment old fellow, that will trouble me. Let's away. The Queen (I ſuppoſe) will by this time expect you. Think over what I 've told you.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt Prieſt and Evad.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Geron ſol.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Geron.</speaker>
                  <p>And have not I brought my ſelf into a ſweet condition now? — Heavens! nothing grieveth me but that I am an old fool. Why, could not I remember how many I had cuckold my ſelf? and to think I ſhould not be ſerved in the ſame kind if ever I married, was to ſuppoſe nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wickedneſs nor juſtice in the world. How could I ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that any one of the lower rate of Court-Ladies would ever keep her ſelf honeſt three minutes, when once ſhe feared neither the danger of taking Savine, nor a big-belly? With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all doubt, now the Prieſt hath given her leave to eat fleſh, ſhe runs from diſh to diſh, like a ſtarved priſoner at a feaſt, who for three months hath had only the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to think of meat; and that's the reaſon her belly is ſo ſoon full. I might have been theſe four years a getting her — by the rate I went to work with her; but now (I think) I could do it with my horns, were it to do again. Ah! <hi>Geron, Geron!</hi> What a cocks-comb art thou in thy old age? A reverent fool! How prettily do horns min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle with thy gray hairs? And yet thou art likely to cauſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:54200:10"/>more laughter then a wit. Heaven! What a condition am I in? My Lord <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> he's a man of an aſpiring ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and of what elſe, the world may imagine; but my head muſt have a hard bargain of it. My Lord <hi>Edymion</hi> he's a Poet, forſooth, and can finde no other place but my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend fore-head for his forked <hi>Parnaſſus.</hi> And for my Lord <hi>Neander,</hi> the Prieſt convinced him the other day that adultery was a very great ſin; and that is reaſon enough for him to lie at rack and manger. What a conſpiracie is there here to make me a cuckold? O that I had now but the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity to hang my ſelf? Now do I perfectly perceive the pains that poor Children indure at the coming of their teeth, by the coming of my horns. How happy was I when I was a young man, when my care was only to keep my hair from forking, and I gave every Barber a fee for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit: but Oh that I had got but one receit to keep my head from forking, in this my old age! Wicked <hi>Phroneſia,</hi> How haſt thou uſed me? How haſt thou affronted my weakneſs, that thou haſt made a collection through all the Court for a big-belly?—But, what a comfortable ſight will it be to me, to ſee her lie in? what a deal of pleaſure I ſhall take to pay the Midwife and Nource? Well, it is now in my own power to make my ſelf maz'd imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately. O, O, O.</p>
                  <l>I muſt away, I muſt. But ah! I dread</l>
                  <l>I near ſhall get theſe horns out of my head.—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Geron as in a fury.</stage>
               <trailer>Finis Act. prim.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:54200:10"/>
               <head>Actus 2. Scoena 1.</head>
               <stage>Enter Pyrrhus and Urania, as in a Garden.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <p>—VVEll, Madam <hi>Urania!</hi> You imagine my buſineſs. As long as you are pretty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> folks will be amorous. You know my meaning.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ran.</speaker>
                  <l>The Heavens forbid.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>Sure 'tis the twentieth time I've told you it,</l>
                  <l>And muſt you hear it o'er again once more?</l>
                  <l>I hope my buſineſs then is almoſt done,</l>
                  <l>When thus you love the repetition of it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ran.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord! Oh add not injury to my misfortune!—</l>
                  <l>Oh! pity; rather pity a poor Girl</l>
                  <l>Who fain would ſeem to be as innocent</l>
                  <l>As late ſhe was, and not to underſtand</l>
                  <l>How harmleſs words by men are turn'd to ſins.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>Why ſhould you be thus obſtinate? To be</l>
                  <l>A Miſtreſs to a King; what greater honour</l>
                  <l>Can thoſe you ſerve ere hop'e t'aſpire to?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ran.</speaker>
                  <l>A Miſtreſs to a King! No, no, you'd have me</l>
                  <l>To be a Servant to his vice; an honour</l>
                  <l>I ſhould not envie her that ſought my ruine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>Is love a vice, <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania?</hi> Then ſurely nature</l>
                  <l>Did make us vitious when ſhe did immerſe</l>
                  <l>Love in the very beings of all Creatures.</l>
                  <l>Search the great Univerſe, and ſhew me there</l>
                  <l>What (but affrighted man) is not as free</l>
                  <l>To ſatisfie his loves, as thirſt or hunger?</l>
                  <l>They near diſpute the lawfulneſs of what</l>
                  <l>Is natural. No ſtone was e'er ſo dull</l>
                  <l>To make't a caſe of conſcience whether it</l>
                  <l>Should follow 'ts natural motion to the Centre.</l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:54200:11"/>
                  <l>Love's natures repreſentative, to whom ſhe ſeems</l>
                  <l>To 've taught her Trade, and inſtituted it</l>
                  <l>Still to continue all her ſelf had made;</l>
                  <l>Without which (ſurely) this whole world had been</l>
                  <l>But one poor Generation, and each ſpecies</l>
                  <l>Had been made up but of one He and She.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ran.</speaker>
                  <l>You do do well, my Lord, when you intend</l>
                  <l>Unlawful loves, to inſtance not in men</l>
                  <l>But beaſts.—But let me ever be</l>
                  <l>Of that affrighted number who follow vertue,</l>
                  <l>Rather then your examples with four feet.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>Miſtaken Sophiſtreſs! How much more powerfully</l>
                  <l>Doſt thou diſpute with thoſe ſoft eyes of thine,</l>
                  <l>Then with thy pretty tongue? Let theſe then be</l>
                  <l>Rather imploy'd to ſee thy errour, then</l>
                  <l>This to defend it. Know, that inſtances</l>
                  <l>In beaſts, do hold in men, when they relate</l>
                  <l>Unto that Nature which is truely common</l>
                  <l>Unto them both: And ſuch is this of Love.</l>
                  <l>They cannot Say their paſſions like to us,</l>
                  <l>But they can Meane them with as ſtrong an Ardor.</l>
                  <l>And though they do not ſing their loves in verſe,</l>
                  <l>Like me; they do attain them leſs in proſe.</l>
                  <l>And is this wickedneſs! Sure vice is known</l>
                  <l>By its own fruit; and what do theſe bring forth?</l>
                  <l>Thy ſheep <hi>Urania,</hi> gave thee gentle Lambs,</l>
                  <l>The warmer Goat brought forth a prity Kid</l>
                  <l>That thou wouldſt play withal: And wilt thou blame</l>
                  <l>That play which did produce thy play-fellow?</l>
                  <l>No, no, <hi>Urania!</hi> Love, like men, was free,</l>
                  <l>Ere power and laws had taught them both the uſe</l>
                  <l>Of chaynes and fetters (Nature ne'er confin'd</l>
                  <l>Her nobleſt creature to the narroweſt priſon,</l>
                  <l>Nor gave him inclinations to torment him)</l>
                  <l>And therefore when thy Prince, who only doth</l>
                  <l>In right abridge thy other liberties,</l>
                  <l>Shall offer to reſtore thee this, thou maiſt</l>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:54200:11"/>
                  <l>As freely take it as thou might'ſt the reſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ran.</speaker>
                  <l>How is the King (my Lord) oblig'd unto you,</l>
                  <l>To ſerve whom, even in ſin, you can permit</l>
                  <l>Your nobleſt faculties to abuſe each other,</l>
                  <l>Your Reaſon to abuſe your Love? But ſay, my Lord!</l>
                  <l>Do you do well to plant ſo mighty Engines</l>
                  <l>Againſt ſo weak a Fort, that is deſign'd</l>
                  <l>Only a poor ſhelter unto Innocence?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>Well, <hi>Urania!</hi> I do perceive you ſtill</l>
                  <l>Make me to toil in vain: But (though 'tis hard</l>
                  <l>And painful to deliver harder dooms</l>
                  <l>To pretty folks) yet I muſt plainly tell you,</l>
                  <l>The King's reſolv'd to leave you but this choice,</l>
                  <l>Either to Love, or Die; to be the Subject</l>
                  <l>Of his Revenge or Pleaſure: anſwer quickly,</l>
                  <l>And anſwer wiſely<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For (believ't <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi>)</l>
                  <l>If you refuſe his Love, this houre's your laſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ran.</speaker>
                  <l>Sure Sir, the King's more juſt—
<stage>She cries.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>By Heaven it's true.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ran.</speaker>
                  <l>Then Heavens more merciful—Unfortunate,</l>
                  <l>Unfortunate <hi>Urania,</hi> what canſt thou do?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>What? Thou canſt grant the Kings deſires, and live.—</l>
                  <l>Come, be brief. Here's one at hand will have ſmall pity on you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ran.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh, my Lord, pity me! pity a diſtreſſed Maid.</l>
                  <stage>She kneels.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania,</hi> pity your ſelf, and pity a Prince that loves you.</l>
                  <l>Come, do not caſt away thy ſelf: You're young,</l>
                  <l>And (if you pleaſe) have many years to live,</l>
                  <l>And pleaſant ones. Be wiſe ere't be too late.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Uran.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, what ſhall I do?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>Why love the King.</l>
                  <l>Say but the word, and hee'l preſently be here.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ran.</speaker>
                  <l>And muſt I looſe my Innocence?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>Come, come,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Urania</hi> live. The King will ſtreight be with you.</l>
                  <l>I'le turn the Lock, and keep you ſure till then.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Ex.</hi> Pyrrh. <hi>and locks the door.</hi>
               </stage>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:54200:12"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ran. ſol.</speaker>
                  <l>Unhappy Maid; wretched <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thou art undone, for evermore undone.</l>
                  <l>Loſt to the World, or Innocence. Thy choice</l>
                  <l>Is either to be wicked, or to die;</l>
                  <l>To looſe thy Virginpurity, or life.</l>
                  <l>Ay me, unbleſt! What black, what fatal Star</l>
                  <l>Shone ſad misfortune at thy birth? How happy,</l>
                  <l>How bleſt hadſt thou been ſtill, hadſt thou ſtill dwelt</l>
                  <l>'Mongſt thoſe who wear poor cloaths, and honour Vertue;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe chaſter Loves made Love a Deity.</l>
                  <l>What will thy Mother ſay, when ſhe ſhall hear</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi> is not Innocent? And what</l>
                  <l>Will thy brave Love think, who ne'er approacht thee</l>
                  <l>But with a flame as pure as that which burns</l>
                  <l>On holy <hi>Veſta</hi>'s Altars. No, no; die,</l>
                  <l>Die, die, unfortunate, but chaſte <hi>Urania.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Never be thrifty of that blood which muſt</l>
                  <l>But ſerve to bluſh that it preſerv'd it ſelf.</l>
                  <l>Endymion <hi>from behind an Arbor</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>—'Tis not ſafe to tarry longer. Poor Soul, her love</l>
                  <l>To me may prove her ruine. Now I ſee</l>
                  <l>She loves me, and I muſt improve my time.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>He appears.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My dear <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania!</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>— Why theſe Tears?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Uran.</speaker>
                  <l>Is this <hi>Endymions</hi> Ghoſt?—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>No, 'tis his Body, Madam.—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>He imbraceth her.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ran.</speaker>
                  <l>Then ne'er more welcome.</l>
                  <l>Dear my Lord! <hi>Urania</hi> is undone.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>Not ſo, becauſe <hi>Endymion</hi> lives.—Know,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Urania</hi>'s ruine never can be writ</l>
                  <l>But in <hi>Endymions</hi> blood.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Uran.</speaker>
                  <l>Undone beyond</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Endymions</hi> help, becauſe to help her is</l>
                  <l>To be a Traytor now.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>If to aſſiſt</l>
                  <l>My Queen be to rebell, then let me wear</l>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:54200:12"/>
                  <l>The glorious Name of Traytor.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ran.</speaker>
                  <l>Ah! my Lord,</l>
                  <l>You know not what I mean.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, yes, my Dear,</l>
                  <l>Yond Arbor was my covert, whilſt I heard</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> aſſault thy Noble Innocence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Uran.</speaker>
                  <l>And can you help me now, my Lord?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>I can;</l>
                  <l>And I will ſhew you how I can. — But know,</l>
                  <l>Know my <hi>Urania,</hi> I have lov'd thee long,</l>
                  <l>And lov'd thee with a holy flame. My Hopes</l>
                  <l>And all my Longings have as vertuous been,</l>
                  <l>As thoſe of pious Votaries, who court</l>
                  <l>Strait-lac'd Religion. All my ſighs and tears</l>
                  <l>Have been as pure, as are thoſe Gales and Springs,</l>
                  <l>That in <hi>Elyſium</hi> do refreſh the Bleſt.</l>
                  <l>And yet thou haſt not pitied him that loves thee,</l>
                  <l>Even though thy very Nature be as gentle</l>
                  <l>As Morning dew juſt melting into Ayr.</l>
                  <l>And ſhall I languiſh thus, and die? Muſt Love</l>
                  <l>His Martyrs have, as well as other Gods?</l>
                  <l>Sure no, <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania;</hi> he hath no Rewards</l>
                  <l>Beyond this Life: How can he gratifie</l>
                  <l>His Martyrs then? The cold Inhabitants</l>
                  <l>Of Graves do not deſire, but dwell alone,</l>
                  <l>And never Think, like aged Prieſts and Nuns.</l>
                  <l>Help then thy dying Lover, and he'll change</l>
                  <l>His Love to adoration, ſince thou wantſt</l>
                  <l>Nothing but pity to become Divine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Uran.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſhall I ſerve you in, my Lord?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>Permit</l>
                  <l>Me to enjoy the Title of thy Servant;</l>
                  <l>And pay my fire with equal flames again.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Uran.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, I were ungrateful if I ſhould not.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>Then be not ſo. — But (to be ſhort) I doubt</l>
                  <l>The Kings approach; and therefore, if thou'lt promiſe</l>
                  <l>This night to ſleep within mine Arms (being firſt</l>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:54200:13"/>
                  <l>Authoriz'd ſo to do by <hi>Hymen</hi>'s Prieſt)</l>
                  <l>I'le free thee from the Kings illicite Love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ran.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, I will. But ſatisfie me how.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>You muſt appoint the King to meet you here</l>
                  <l>In yonder Grotto, and oblige him to</l>
                  <l>The language, and the time of Love, ſoft whiſpers,</l>
                  <l>And the Night; and I'll prepare</l>
                  <l>Some other Body to ſupply your place.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ran.</speaker>
                  <l>Ah! Who will be ſo wicked as to do't?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>Enough.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ran.</speaker>
                  <l>Sure 'tis impoſſible, it cannot be.</l>
                  <l>What Woman would conſent to ſuch an Act?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>Ten thouſand, Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ran.</speaker>
                  <l>Would they? They let them not—</l>
                  <l>I'll rather chuſe a thouſand times to die,</l>
                  <l>Then own a wretched life, ſav'd at the Rate</l>
                  <l>Of ſo much Wickedneſs.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>Come; be content,</l>
                  <l>Chaſte Soul, the Queen her ſelf ſhall be the Perſon.</l>
                  <l>I'll tell her all thy ſtory, and I doubt not</l>
                  <l>But ſhe'll preſerve thy Innocence, and love it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Uran.</speaker>
                  <l>Thrive, brave <hi>Endymion;</hi> thrive in all thy Loves,</l>
                  <l>That haſt for Love redeem'd (and redeem'd too</l>
                  <l>Without a Sacrifice) a wretched Maid,</l>
                  <l>Nought but whoſe Blood could have preſerv'd her White.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>My Dear, I muſt retire: I fear the King.</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt a Part to act, and ſo have I.</l>
                  <l>Be happy, fair <hi>Urania;</hi> I am bleſt</l>
                  <l>That my imployment is to do thee ſervice.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Ex.</hi> Endym. <hi>as at a private door.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Uran. ſol.</speaker>
                  <l>Poor, poor <hi>Endymion!</hi> in what little point</l>
                  <l>Will all the Vertue and Religion end</l>
                  <l>Of thy contrivances? How doth thy Fate,</l>
                  <l>In the contempt of all that's brave and worthy,</l>
                  <l>Play with thy Noble Actions; and endeavour</l>
                  <l>In pride to make Vertue ridiculous?</l>
                  <l>Poor, poor, <hi>Endymion!</hi> How could I now weep,</l>
                  <l>If tears were able but to waſh away</l>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:54200:13"/>
                  <l>The blackneſs of thy Fate? Now thou haſt thought</l>
                  <l>(And thought by paths white as the milky-way)</l>
                  <l>To lead me from the Labyrinth of my Woes;</l>
                  <l>The next thing I muſt think, muſt be to cheat</l>
                  <l>All thy innocent expectations, which</l>
                  <l>Are every of them Honours to my ſelf,</l>
                  <l>And condeſcentions in thy Noble Soul.</l>
                  <l>Whilſt thou in melting language tell'ſt my tale,</l>
                  <l>And giv'ſt me ſo much value by thy words,</l>
                  <l>That ſhe who is a Queen ſhall condeſcend</l>
                  <l>(And love that condeſcention too) to pity</l>
                  <l>The Daughter of an humble Villager,</l>
                  <l>And to become her ſelf her Subſtitute:</l>
                  <l>Whilſt thou doſt this (and for no recompence,</l>
                  <l>But to beſtow on me, what were more fit</l>
                  <l>For Temples far, a pure unſpotted Love)</l>
                  <l>I muſt endeavour at that very time</l>
                  <l>To fruſtrate all thy hopes, and only give</l>
                  <l>My fained promiſe to the King, on this</l>
                  <l>Condition, That <hi>Endymion</hi> muſt be ſent</l>
                  <l>So far from Court, that he do not return</l>
                  <l>Until to morrow Sun ſee us again,</l>
                  <l>And my engagement to him be made void.</l>
                  <l>And to effect my purpoſe the more ſurely,</l>
                  <l>I muſt endeavour to perſwade the King</l>
                  <l>That he hath often courted me, and hath</l>
                  <l>So wary eyes upon me, that I doubt</l>
                  <l>I ſhall not be ſecure but by his abſence;</l>
                  <l>And thus I muſt reward the brave <hi>Endymion.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But, I will recompence thee with my tears:</l>
                  <l>And ſince I cannot ſat is fie thy flame,</l>
                  <l>I'll weep it out.— Poor, poor <hi>Endymion!</hi>
                     <stage>She weeps.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>How muſt I cry to ſee thee like a Ball</l>
                  <l>Toſs'd vainly up and down, even by thoſe two</l>
                  <l>Blinde Gameſters, <hi>Love,</hi> and <hi>Fortune?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Pyrrhus.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>And why with ſhowres allay you thus you beams?</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:54200:14"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Uran.</speaker>
                  <l>You are the Meſſenger of Sorrow, Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>In bringing the ſad news a Prince attends</l>
                  <l>Your prettineſs in yonder Parler. Come. —</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>He takes her by the hand.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Uran.</speaker>
                  <l>I'll follow, Sir. — Pray Sir go on, I'll follow.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>I'm glad you're ſo obedient.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Urania <hi>to her ſelf.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Urania!</speaker>
                  <l>Whiter goeſt thou? With what face</l>
                  <l>Canſt thou ſay Yes unto the Kings propoſals,</l>
                  <l>Although thou ſurely doſt intend to cheat him?</l>
                  <l>It is immodeſt ſure. — It cannot fit</l>
                  <l>A Maiden mouth.— I never more muſt pray</l>
                  <l>With the ſame tongue that's able (though but fain'd)</l>
                  <l>Thus to conſent. —</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>She ſtops.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, I muſt have your hand, unleſs you'll follow.</l>
                  <l>Uran. <hi>to her ſelf.</hi> Kind Heaven aſſiſt me! — Give me ſtrength to hear</l>
                  <l>— What I ſhould not, and fain'dly to aſſent.</l>
                  <l>And know, Heaven, like thy Sun, my bluſhes ſhall</l>
                  <l>This Even ſhew, I will riſe fair to morrow.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Exeunt</hi> Uran. <hi>and</hi> Pyrrhus.</stage>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Neander <hi>and</hi> Evadne, <hi>with a Maid following her at a diſtance.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <l>— And what d'ye think of thoſe unactive houres</l>
                  <l>You've ſpent in Cells, compar'd to thoſe o'th<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Court?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Evadne.</speaker>
                  <l>I think them innocent. And if they ſhew'd</l>
                  <l>Me fewer objects, they did ſhew me too</l>
                  <l>Fewer temptations, and therefore gave me</l>
                  <l>More content, though leſs variety.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, the divers objects of the Court</l>
                  <l>Have yet been but diſturbances, to ſcatter</l>
                  <l>Thoſe thoughts of yours which your dim Cell united.</l>
                  <l>But when you've weigh'd each various face, each garb,</l>
                  <l>Each brisk behaviour <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>mongſt the Gallants here,</l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:54200:14"/>
                  <l>And have contracted your now ſcatter'd beams</l>
                  <l>To make illuſtrious ſome one perſons fortune;</l>
                  <l>You'll then take pleaſure in your own effects,</l>
                  <l>This day to frown him dead, to morrow to</l>
                  <l>Kiſs him alive again; and thus each day</l>
                  <l>To multiply the Miracles of Love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Evadne.</speaker>
                  <l>Theſe are the Wonders Sir, which greater Beauties</l>
                  <l>Do in far higher Orbs: <hi>Evadne</hi> were</l>
                  <l>Proud, as her Fortune hath deſign'd her low,</l>
                  <l>Should ſhe dare think ought what in complement</l>
                  <l>You do attribute to her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, would you were but content</l>
                  <l>To ſee me fall your earlieſt Victim here.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Evad.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas, my Lord, the Sacrifice would much</l>
                  <l>Excell the Deity.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <l>No more then little Fanes,</l>
                  <l>The mighty powers they're dedicate to.—</l>
                  <l>Deareſt <hi>Evadne,</hi> faireſt Murdreſs, thou</l>
                  <l>Haſt ſlain <hi>Neander</hi> with thy pretty eyes.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>He imbraceth her with his arme.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Evad.</speaker>
                  <l>And do you apprehend me for it, Sir?</l>
                  <l>What Flower is yonder?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>She goes from him to gather it.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <l>A Flower more happy (Madam) then my ſelf,</l>
                  <l>And like me ſhews you do love cruelty;</l>
                  <l>That fain would live, and you to kill it, place</l>
                  <l>It in your Boſome. I would fain live too,</l>
                  <l>And you to kill me, thence will keep me out.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Evad.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, though I am wholly ignorant</l>
                  <l>Of all the Arts of Court, yet I can ſee</l>
                  <l>You're pleas'd to fain much Love, to exerciſe</l>
                  <l>Much Wit. Surely, I cannot think</l>
                  <l>You can ſo ſoon be taken with my Beauty.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <l>Then hear my Vowes.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Evad.</speaker>
                  <l>No, good my Lord, let theſe</l>
                  <l>On more deliberation be pronounc'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <l>Do men deliberate whether they will be</l>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:54200:15"/>
                  <l>Happy and bleſt? — Pox on this Rogue.—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Geron <hi>to them.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Geron.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, now I will not hang my ſelf yet, I'le be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veng'd on this Lord firſt.—My Lord—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſay you <hi>Geron?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Geron.</speaker>
                  <p>— How do you do, my Lord?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <p>Very well, <hi>Geron.</hi> How doth your Lady?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Get. <hi>ſtamps and ſpeaks to himſelf.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>'Tis he hath done it.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <p>Why? How now, <hi>Geron;</hi> Do you conjure? What's the matter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger. <hi>to himſelf.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>I need not conjure. I know the Father now.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, what doſt thou mutter among thy no teeth, Man?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, why ſhould you ask for my Wife?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe I am civil.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger. <hi>to himſelf.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe I am a Cuckold.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <p>Pox on thee, why doſt not ſpeak out?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <p>Ah—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <p>Prithee <hi>Geron,</hi> what's the matter? Haſt thou ſeen a Spirit? Or haſt thou loſt any money? What is it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Evadne.</speaker>
                  <p>Your ſervant, Sir.—I ſuppoſe by this time my Lord <hi>Endymion</hi> will have left the Queen.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <p>So very haſty Madam! You will permit me to wait on your Ladiſhip. Fare you well, <hi>Geron.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Exeunt</hi> Neand<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>and</hi> Evadne.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ceron. ſol.</speaker>
                  <p>This is the Man.— 'Tis he.— Why ſhould he ask for my Wife? Suppoſe I have a VVife, what's that to him? Muſt be needs be asking for her preſently? Ah <hi>phro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſia,</hi> I wiſh (I wiſh heartily) I had never ſeen the head of thee,— But, I could never be content till I was married, like a fool as I was,— This Raſcal <hi>Neander;</hi> this Raſcal that I dare nor call Raſcal: This Villain that I dare not ſay any thing to, not becauſe he is Valiant (for then it would not grieve me) but becauſe he is a Lord, which he could no more help then I can that he hath made me a Cuckold. He was born to that, juſt as I am to this. The caſe is the ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame.—</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Endymion.</stage>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:54200:15"/>
               <l>— Here's another Lord too.—</l>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir <hi>Geron,</hi> how is it with you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Geron.</speaker>
                  <p>Your Servant, my Lord.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eudym.</speaker>
                  <p>How doth the fair <hi>Phroneſia,</hi> Sir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger. to himſelf.</speaker>
                  <p>What! Here's another.— Two Lords to make one Cuckold.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <p>What, mute, <hi>Geron!</hi> Hath any misfortune befallen your Wife?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger. to himſelf.</speaker>
                  <p>Cuckold! Laught at! —</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Geron,</hi> you make me wonder. —</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger. to himſelf ſtill.</speaker>
                  <p>You have made me a Cuckold I am ſure, among you.—</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter a Page haſtily; and delivers a Letter to</hi> Endymion <hi>from the King: at which he withdraweth a little, and opens it.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Geron.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, I ſhall take my leave of you; you have buſineſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Exeunt Geron</hi> and <hi>Page.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Endym. <hi>reads the Letter: which was,</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <floatingText type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                           <hi>We are informed (though not certainly) that there happened laſt night a mutiny in Our Caſtle of</hi> Argos. <hi>It is Our pleaſure therefore, that you, immediately on ſight hereof, take a conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent number of Our Light-horſe, and go thither. And if you finde any ſuch thing, to uſe your beſt endeavours to appeaſe it; and bring with you the principall Actors therein, to receive ſuch puniſhment as their Crimes ſhall deſerve.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Baſileus Rex.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>Where, where will not Misfortune finde thee out?</l>
                  <l>Sure Fortune hath more eyes then thoſe who ſay</l>
                  <l>Shee'th none: elſe how could ſhe ſtill hit the ſelf-ſame mark?</l>
                  <l>This night, when I ſuppos'd within thy armes,</l>
                  <l>Thy armes, my Dear, to have ſcorn'd all the world,</l>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:54200:16"/>
                  <l>To've pitied Monarchs, and lookt down on Kings;</l>
                  <l>Muſt I be taken from my vertuous Love,</l>
                  <l>And change her Starrs (her faireſt Starrs) for thoſe</l>
                  <l>Poore eyes that Heaven allowes to look upon</l>
                  <l>The dewy night withall? — But ſtay; I ſin,</l>
                  <l>I ſin like all the world, who never think</l>
                  <l>That every other part is well, if but</l>
                  <l>One finger pain them.— I am fortunate,</l>
                  <l>That I have gain'd her love, that can no more</l>
                  <l>Change, then a Star his courſe, or Fate</l>
                  <l>Her everlaſting Lawes: and I'm to faile</l>
                  <l>But one night of my promiſe; and that night</l>
                  <l>Is but twelve hours.—But ſay, <hi>Endymion,</hi> how</l>
                  <l>Canſt thou live twelve hours from <hi>Urania</hi>'s eyes?—</l>
                  <l>But I muſt haſte, and bid my Faire adieu.—</l>
                  <l>—And yet I will not neither; the firſt kiſs</l>
                  <l>I begg from thoſe dear lips, ſhall never be</l>
                  <l>A parting one.— And muſt I not then wiſh</l>
                  <l>For a Good-night, becauſe I muſt have none?</l>
                  <l>Sure, I muſt ſee her.—But ſay, <hi>Endymion,</hi> ſay</l>
                  <l>She ſhould look ſad, or ſigh when thou depart'ſt?</l>
                  <l>How doſt thou think, at the ſame time, to quell</l>
                  <l>Two inſurrections, that at <hi>Argos,</hi> and</l>
                  <l>This ſadder one in thy own breaſt? — My Dear,</l>
                  <l>I muſt not ſee thee. I muſt onely make</l>
                  <l>Some little paper happier then my ſelf,</l>
                  <l>And write thee, why <hi>Endymion</hi> is unbleſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Endym.</stage>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> King <hi>and</hi> Pyrrhus.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <p>Well <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> now our buſineſs is done. This night <hi>Urania</hi> (after all her pretty bluſhes, and loathneſs to ſay Yes) is mine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                  <p>She is, an't pleaſe your Majeſty, and I am very glad of it, knowing your Majeſty's paſſion; for the truth is, I did very much doubt ſo much innocence would never have been overcome.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:54200:16"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <p>She was loath indeed.— But <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> prithee ſee <hi>Endymion</hi> loyter not. She was very paſſionate in that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular; and all her promiſe is void, if he be in towne by ſix of the clock this Even: and it is neere ſo much already, I think.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhall haſten him, if he be not already gone.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <p>And then you muſt ſee yond Grotto prepared.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                  <p>It ſhall be fitted for the Scene of Love.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <p>The all I have to do, is to make ſome fair pretence to the Queen for my abſence this night— Look where ſhe comes.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Queen alone.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhall make haſte to wait on your commands.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Ex. Pyrrh.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <p>How doth my Queen? what, all alone?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                  <l>Not now</l>
                  <l>When I have found my Lord, who is to me</l>
                  <l>All company.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Ah! thou haſt found him none.</l>
                  <l>Thou'ſt found him now diſorder'd.— I'm not well.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas, I doubt you've taken cold.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>I have;</l>
                  <l>But hope that this nights reſt will make me well.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>Sure Sir, you don't do well to tarry here.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>I do not, Madam; I'll retire. Good night.
<stage>Kiſſeth her.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, give me leave Sir to attend you.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>No,</l>
                  <l>I will not draw you from the entertainment</l>
                  <l>This pleaſant evening will afford you here.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas, my Prince, you injure now your Queen,</l>
                  <l>To think that evening which gives Pain to you,</l>
                  <l>Can give her Pleaſure.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>My dear, I am not ſick;</l>
                  <l>I onely am a little indiſpos'd;</l>
                  <l>I'll beg thy pardon to retire this night:</l>
                  <l>But pray ſup you, and take no farther care,</l>
                  <l>Till at your own appartment I wait on you</l>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:54200:17"/>
                  <l>To morrow morning.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                  <l>Your will is ſtill my Law.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Once more goodnight.—
<stage>Ex. King.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Queen ſol.</speaker>
                  <l>Poore Prince! poore Prince! How little doſt thou think</l>
                  <l>How ſoon we two ſhall meet again: and ſhe</l>
                  <l>Thou ſo much fly'ſt, ſhall prove the very thing</l>
                  <l>For which thou fly'ſt her? How ridiculous</l>
                  <l>Juſt Heaven doth make the wayes of men, when they</l>
                  <l>Forſake the wayes of Vertue? — This brave Prince,</l>
                  <l>At whoſe victorious Armies <hi>Greece</hi> now trembles,</l>
                  <l>When he contrives inglorious actions, ſhall</l>
                  <l>At the ſame time be pitied by his ſervants;</l>
                  <l>And a poor Girle ſhall upbraid him, in</l>
                  <l>Contriving to preſerve him vertuous.</l>
                  <l>How do men ravel back to childhood, when</l>
                  <l>They ceaſe to be thy Children, ſacred Vertue;</l>
                  <l>And need the care of every little perſon,</l>
                  <l>That what they call for may not do them harm!</l>
                  <l>Poor Prince! I pity thee.—And oh that Heaven</l>
                  <stage>Shee kneeles.</stage>
                  <l>May do ſo too! And though the ſetting Sun</l>
                  <l>Bode nought but darkneſs to the world, yet may</l>
                  <l>Some charitable Star vouchſafe one beam</l>
                  <l>To his benighted breaſt; leſt wicked men</l>
                  <l>Upbraid your wiſdome, that give Crowns and Scepters</l>
                  <l>To thoſe poor ſpirits, who can ſoftly creep</l>
                  <l>At cowardly midnight to their beds of ſin.
<stage>She riſeth.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>How happy ſhould I be this tedious night</l>
                  <l>In yonder Grotto, to expect in vain?</l>
                  <l>And by my penance there to expiate</l>
                  <l>Th' intended crime of my repenting Prince?—</l>
                  <l>But I muſt haſte— Bleſt Heaven, have pity on</l>
                  <l>The folly of my poor deluded Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit. Queen.</stage>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:54200:17"/>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Cleantha. <hi>She takes two or three turns in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and then breaks into theſe words.</hi>
               </stage>
               <l>Unfortunate <hi>Cleantha.</hi> —</l>
               <stage>She walks a turn or two more.</stage>
               <l>—Too fortunate</l>
               <l>In that which Fools call Happineſſe.—</l>
               <stage>She walks a little.</stage>
               <l>—Fate, Fate,</l>
               <l>VVhy doſt thou thus abuſe the world, to make</l>
               <l>Some high, ſome low, yet every one alike</l>
               <l>Unhappy?— whate'er our ſtations be,</l>
               <l>VVe meet in this ſad Center, <hi>Miſery.</hi>—</l>
               <l>Yet, leſt by knowing this, we ſhould rebel,</l>
               <l>And every Generous ſoul turn Deſtiny</l>
               <l>Unto it ſelf, (ſcorning thy tyranny,</l>
               <l>And rather chuſing not to be at all,</l>
               <l>Then be thy ſport) thou haſt contriv'd things ſo,</l>
               <l>That every perſon thinks others more happy,</l>
               <l>And that no breaſt knowes Miſery like theirs.</l>
               <l>But thoſe whom thou doſt deſtine to ſuch Plagues,</l>
               <l>As would break forth through private windows, thou</l>
               <l>Doſt place in mighty Palaces, and with</l>
               <l>External ſplendour hid'ſt their inward Griefs</l>
               <l>From common eyes, and mak'ſt them (ſilly ſouls)</l>
               <l>Admire, what, did they underſtand, they'd pity.</l>
               <l>How many that behold <hi>Cleantha</hi> walk,</l>
               <l>Attended by the proudeſt ſparks of <hi>Greece,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And richer clad then Tulips in the Spring,</l>
               <l>Do think her every minute happier far</l>
               <l>Then Cowards condemn'd are, when their pardon's read;</l>
               <l>And every Lady in <hi>Arcadia</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But wretched, when compar'd to her bright Fortune.</l>
               <l>VVhilſt poor <hi>Cleantha</hi> at that very minute</l>
               <l>Envies ſome Village-Maid that Ruſſet weares</l>
               <l>(The Livery of thoſe ſheep ſhe doth attend)</l>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:54200:18"/>
               <l>But freely favours the poor Swain ſhe loves,</l>
               <l>And ſleeps at night.— <hi>Cleantha</hi>'s oft admir'd,</l>
               <l>And her great titles reckon'd up, whileſt ſhe</l>
               <l>Doth in her cloſet weep ſhe is not leſs.—</l>
               <l>Heaven! Heaven! where was thy Mercy then,</l>
               <l>VVhen thou mad'ſt Life ſo great a pain, and Death</l>
               <l>A Sin?— Didſt thou create great ſouls but to</l>
               <l>Affront them with thy greater power?— But ſtay,</l>
               <l>Prophane <hi>Cleantha,</hi> ſtay; and be not more</l>
               <l>Unfortunate, by being wicked too.—</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Endymion</hi> is all vertue, and he would</l>
               <l>Hate a prophane <hi>Cleantha.</hi>— Poor <hi>Endymion,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How little dar'ſt thou think my thoughts, or I</l>
               <l>Dare ſay them to thee?— Ah wretched, wretched Princeſs,</l>
               <l>VVhom Fate hath made greater then Happineſs!—</l>
               <l>VVhat can I hope for? ſhould <hi>Endymion</hi> ſpeak,</l>
               <l>I then ſhould hate him for his confidence;</l>
               <l>A Crime, of which he never can be guilty.—</l>
               <l>VVhen once he bled for me (and conquer'd too)</l>
               <l>And I on purpoſe chid my woman, that</l>
               <l>She was unhandy, onely 'cauſe my hand</l>
               <l>Ambitious was to wipe his wounds, and give</l>
               <l>Him Balſam for the better Balſam of</l>
               <l>His blood; poor Lord, me thought he ſeem'd to wiſh</l>
               <l>The earth had been created lower, that</l>
               <l>He might have lower bow'd, to give me thanks;</l>
               <l>And was ſo far from daring to preſume,</l>
               <l>That he did ſeem to make the diſtance more</l>
               <l>Betwixt himſelf and me, by placing me</l>
               <l>Yet higher, for my ſo great charity.</l>
               <l>Nay, ſhould he ſpeak, in ſpeaking he would forfeit</l>
               <l>The very thing I love him for, that reſt</l>
               <l>He findes in th' Elyſium of his thoughts;</l>
               <l>And thoſe true ſatisfactions which he takes,</l>
               <l>In being all the world unto himſelf.</l>
               <l>But ſince my Love is vertuous as its Object<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>VVhy ſhould I ſtick to tell it all the world?</l>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:54200:18"/>
               <l>Nay, why ſhould I not rather glory in it?</l>
               <l>To bluſh to ſay I love <hi>Endymion,</hi> were</l>
               <l>To be aſham'd to love Religion, 'cauſe</l>
               <l>Her Prieſts are poor.— If Fortune 'th ſet him low,</l>
               <l>Fools that are blind, like her, may do ſo too.</l>
               <l>But let <hi>Cleantha</hi>'s pleaſure be to ſee</l>
               <l>Vertue affronting the Fools Deity.</l>
               <l>Direct me, my good Starrs; and let me do</l>
               <l>Honour to him, who ſo much honours you.</l>
               <l>And if I needs ſo hard a Fate muſt prove,</l>
               <l>As fall at laſt a Sacrifice to Love;</l>
               <l>'Twill be my Glory, when it ſhall be ſaid,</l>
               <l>Cleantha <hi>for the brave</hi> Endymion <hi>dy'd.</hi>
               </l>
               <stage>Exit. Cleantha.</stage>
               <trailer>Finis Act. 2.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <head>ACTUS 3.</head>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter King. He takes a turn or two, and then to him</hi> Pyrrhus.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <p>GOod morrow to you, my Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <p>A good day to your Majeſty. A day as pleaſant as your night hath been.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <p>Ah! — I wiſh it indeed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <p>I hope your Majeſty hath been well enough diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this night.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>King.</hi>—</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, my Lord— though not as you ſuppoſe.—</l>
                  <l>I've been diverted from thoſe wild deſires</l>
                  <l>That made me firſt unking my ſelf, and then</l>
                  <l>Unlord my Confident. But I've ask'd pardon</l>
                  <l>Of Heaven and my own Majeſty; and now</l>
                  <l>I beg it too from thee, my loyall <hi>Pyrrhus:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:54200:19"/>
                  <l>Forgive me that I have profan'd thy Faith</l>
                  <l>By ſuch Commands, that thou art bound to ask</l>
                  <l>Bleſt Heaven forgiveneſſe for thy Loyalty.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Majeſty (I hope) will give me leave</l>
                  <l>To wonder at this change, and underſtand it,</l>
                  <l>When you ſhall pleaſe to think me fit to do ſo.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> I'le tell thee all.— VVhen now the night</l>
                  <l>Grew black enough to hide a skulking action;</l>
                  <l>And Heaven had never an eye unſhut to fee</l>
                  <l>Her Repreſentative on earth creep 'mongſt</l>
                  <l>Thoſe poor defenſleſs worms, whom Nature 'th left</l>
                  <l>An humble prey to every thing; and no</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aſylum</hi> but the Dark: I ſoftly ſtole</l>
                  <l>To yonder Grotto through the upper walks,</l>
                  <l>And there found my <hi>Urania,</hi>— But I found her,</l>
                  <l>I found her, <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> not a Miſtreſs, but</l>
                  <l>A Goddeſs rather, which made me now to be</l>
                  <l>No more her Lover, but Idolater.</l>
                  <l>She onely whiſpered to me, as ſhe promis'd,</l>
                  <l>Yet never heard I any voice ſo loud:</l>
                  <l>And though her words were gentler far then thoſe</l>
                  <l>That holy Prieſts do ſpeak to dying Saints,</l>
                  <l>Yet never Thunder ſignified ſo much.</l>
                  <l>And what did more impreſs what e'er ſhe ſaid,</l>
                  <l>Methought her whiſpers were my injur'd Queens,</l>
                  <l>Her manner juſt like hers.— And when ſhe urg'd</l>
                  <l>(Among a thouſand things) the injury</l>
                  <l>I did the faithfull'ſt Princeſs in the world,</l>
                  <l>Who now ſuppos'd me ſick, and was perchance</l>
                  <l>Upon her knees, offering up holy vowes</l>
                  <l>For him who mockt both heaven and her, and was</l>
                  <l>Now breaking of that vow he made her, when</l>
                  <l>With ſacrifice he call'd the Gods to witneſs;</l>
                  <l>When ſhe urg'd this, and wept, and ſpake ſo like</l>
                  <l>My poor deluded Queen, <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> I trembl'd,</l>
                  <l>Almoſt perſwaded that it was her Angel</l>
                  <l>Spake through <hi>Urania</hi>'s lips; who for her ſake</l>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:54200:19"/>
                  <l>Took care of me, as ſomething ſhe much lov'd.</l>
                  <l>It would be long to tell thee all ſhe ſaid,</l>
                  <l>How oft ſhe figh'd, how bitterly ſhe wept:</l>
                  <l>But the effect. <hi>Urania</hi> ſtill is chaſt,</l>
                  <l>And with her chaſter lips hath promis'd to</l>
                  <l>Invoke bleſt Heaven for my intended ſin.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>A happy night. Indeed, I ne'r took pleaſure</l>
                  <l>To've ſerv'd your Majeſty in this employment,</l>
                  <l>Untill this inſtant.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>But how doſt think, my <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I ſhall reward <hi>Urania</hi> for this action?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>Ten thouſand wayes.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>No, no, I am unhappy;</l>
                  <l>I muſt undo the fair, the chaſt <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>And me with wonder too.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou know'ſt ſhe told me</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Endymion</hi> was her ſervant (an high Fortune</l>
                  <l>For one ſo mean, and a rare one too,</l>
                  <l>VVho can love Vertue where he ſees her poor.)</l>
                  <l>And I ſhall be conſtrained to baniſh him</l>
                  <l>To ſome remoter Iſle, unleſſe he'll be</l>
                  <l>(VVhich I much doubt) content to marry her</l>
                  <l>VVithin few dayes. <hi>Pyr.</hi> This is all news. <hi>King.</hi> It is.</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> thou art worthy of my ſecrets.</l>
                  <l>And therefore know, I've lately learnt, <hi>Cleantha</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Loves nothing but <hi>Endymion.</hi> Though ſhe have</l>
                  <l>(Thou know'n) a Prince that courts her, high in Birth</l>
                  <l>And Fortune too: one worthy our alliance,</l>
                  <l>Yet ſhe ſlights all addreſſes, and laſt night</l>
                  <l>I was inform'd, 'was onely for the ſake</l>
                  <l>Of this mean Lord; which ſhould the Prince but know,</l>
                  <l>He ſure would ſcorn her for his Rivals ſake.</l>
                  <l>The certainty I hope to know this day,</l>
                  <l>From our good Prieſt, whom I've employ'd to ſound her,</l>
                  <l>And learn her reſolutions, whence I ſhall</l>
                  <l>Diſcern <hi>Endymions</hi> fate. <hi>Pyr.</hi> An't pleaſe your Majeſty,</l>
                  <l>But doth <hi>Endymion</hi> know <hi>Cleantha</hi> loves him?</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:54200:20"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>I'm told he doth not. All that can be gather'd,</l>
                  <l>Is but from ſome few words ſhe was by chance</l>
                  <l>O'er-heard to ſay unto her ſelf, too big</l>
                  <l>For her own breaſts confinement, and too ſecret</l>
                  <l>(It ſeems) for any others ear.— But heark, what's yonder?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Trumpets without.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                  <l>I doe believe <hi>Endymion</hi> is return'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King</speaker>
                  <l>It's likely. Let us in, and have his anſwer.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Ex. King, Pyrrhus.</stage>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Cleantha ſol. <hi>into the Garden. She walks a while, often fetching very deep ſighs; at laſt ſaith,</hi>
               </stage>
               <l>— When every thing is green,</l>
               <l>Muſt poor <hi>Cleantha</hi> onely wither, and never</l>
               <l>Know a Spring?— Was I made onely high</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Rhodope,</hi> and <hi>Haemus,</hi> or the Alpes,</l>
               <l>To dwell with everlaſting winter, to wear Snow,</l>
               <l>When every valley Roſes wears?— <hi>Cleantha,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thou muſt die. Then thou maiſt alſo be</l>
               <l>Happy as other folks. The Grave looks wiſtly,</l>
               <l>Like thy Fortune. Then every bodies face</l>
               <l>Is pale as thine. There, there thou wilt not ſee</l>
               <l>Poor Villagers more bleſt in love then thee.</l>
               <l>And there thou wilt be able make appear,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cleantha</hi> and <hi>Endymion</hi> equall are.—</l>
               <l>Then, poſſibly, ſome of <hi>Cleantha</hi>'s earth</l>
               <l>May prove a little flower, and look freſher,</l>
               <l>Then when it part of a great Princeſs was,</l>
               <l>And ſhew the erring world —</l>
               <stage>Enter the Prieſt.</stage>
               <l>— Heaven! what ſhall I ſay</l>
               <l>To this good man now?—</l>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pri.</speaker>
                  <l>Good morrow to your Highneſs.</l>
                  <l>Heaven ſend you a good day.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleantha.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhall not doubt it,</l>
                  <l>After ſo good a Prayer.— Good morrow, Sir.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prieſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Highneſs all alone? 'Twere too great boldneſs</l>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:54200:20"/>
                  <l>To aske what little penſiveneſs invited</l>
                  <l>You to ſo much retirement, whilſt the day</l>
                  <l>Is yet ſo young; and you as young as it?—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clean.</speaker>
                  <l>I cannot wonder, Sir, at what you ask,</l>
                  <l>When I conſider in what vanities</l>
                  <l>I uſually have ſpent my mornings, more</l>
                  <l>Examining my Face then Self.— But late
<stage>She ſighs.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Repentance is a little commendable.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pri.</speaker>
                  <l>But yours, Madam, is not ſo. Your morning yet</l>
                  <l>Is younger then this dayes, and you can ſtill</l>
                  <l>Pay Firſt-fruits unto Vertue.— But, fair Princeſs,</l>
                  <l>(Pardon the freedom of your Prieſt) we often</l>
                  <l>Miſtake our Melancholy for Repentance;</l>
                  <l>And think that ſadneſs our ſouls health, which is</l>
                  <l>Indeed, but the diſeaſe of our weak bodies.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                  <l>It's likely, Sir, and likely that weak ſort</l>
                  <l>That I am of, may thus oft be deluded.</l>
                  <l>But Heaven (I hope) hath pity for that weakneſs</l>
                  <l>It made not ſtronger.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prieſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, be pleas'd to know,</l>
                  <l>The onely reaſon why I urge this, is,</l>
                  <l>The onely reaſon why I've thus intruded</l>
                  <l>Into your Highneſſes Retirements now.</l>
                  <l>This is not, Madam, the firſt time I've ſeen</l>
                  <l>Your Highneſs walk alone, and ſhun thoſe places</l>
                  <l>Which company did ſeem to make unhappy:</l>
                  <l>And often have I too obſerv'd you've been</l>
                  <l>Alone i'th' middle of a multitude:</l>
                  <l>Which ſort of temper being no wiſe proper</l>
                  <l>To your more ſprightly age, and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, I</l>
                  <l>(As one oblig'd by Heaven, to ſerve you, and</l>
                  <l>Authori'zd too to ſpeak) preſum'd to watch</l>
                  <l>A fitting opportunity, to pray</l>
                  <l>Your Highneſs to unfold, whether its cauſe</l>
                  <l>No wiſe concerns my Function; or if I</l>
                  <l>Might ſerve you with my Counſel, or my Prayers.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clean.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, You have ever been a Father to me,</l>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:54200:21"/>
                  <l>And, poſſibly, your great reſpect, a little</l>
                  <l>May injure your great judgement, and preſent</l>
                  <l>Things you are pleas'd to fear, as though they were.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prieſt.</speaker>
                  <l>No, Madam, pardon me, I'm not miſtaken;</l>
                  <l>But much more doubt, what you with ſo much art</l>
                  <l>Deſire to hide. Sure, 'tis no common thing</l>
                  <l>You can think worth the covering with ſuch language.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleanth.</speaker>
                  <l>Indeed, I am no wiſe ſad, Sir; you but doubt it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prieſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Pardon me, Madam, if I dare to tell you,</l>
                  <l>You do not well to ſay ſo. You are troubled.—</l>
                  <l>Madam, you are in love.— You ought not to</l>
                  <l>Deny it, 'cauſe 'tis truth.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleanth.</speaker>
                  <l>Nor ought I to</l>
               </sp>
               <l>Confeſs it, 'cauſe it is no ſin.—</l>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prieſt.</speaker>
                  <l>If it be not,</l>
               </sp>
               <l>Indeed you are not bound to't. But if you</l>
               <l>Love one beneath your birth and Fortune, Madam,</l>
               <l>That is a ſin.</l>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleanth.</speaker>
                  <l>It may be ſo; but I</l>
               </sp>
               <l>Am no wiſe guilty of it, Sir.</l>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pri.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam,</l>
               </sp>
               <l>
                  <hi>Endymion</hi> is ſo.—</l>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleanth.</speaker>
                  <l>And can I help it; Sir?</l>
               </sp>
               <l>So are a thouſand more, it may be.—</l>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pri.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam,</l>
                  <l>'Twere to affront your Highneſs, ſhould I longer</l>
                  <l>Delude you by my ſeeming ignorance</l>
                  <l>Of what (would Heaven) had ne'er been known to you,</l>
                  <l>Nor me: Madam, you love that poor</l>
                  <l>Mean Lord <hi>Endymion.</hi>— 'Tis for him that you</l>
                  <l>Look pale, and ſigh, and walk alone, and die</l>
                  <l>To all that's glorious, and worthy you</l>
                  <l>So high a Princeſs.— 'Tis for him you ſlight</l>
                  <l>The Prince of <hi>Macedon,</hi> and diſoblige</l>
                  <l>The King your Unkle.— 'Tis for him you are</l>
                  <l>No more <hi>Cleantha,</hi> no more that noble Princeſs,</l>
                  <l>That like a Deity reflected on</l>
                  <l>Your own perfection (that Supreme Eſtate</l>
                  <l>Nature and Fortune thought you worthy of)</l>
                  <l>And did eſteem your ſelf at the ſame rate</l>
                  <l>Heaven and the Gods had valued you.— But, Madam,</l>
                  <l>'Tis not too late yet to recant all this;</l>
                  <l>And there is oft more glory in repenting</l>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:54200:21"/>
                  <l>Us of ſome errours, then never to have err'd;</l>
                  <l>Becauſe we find, there are more folks have Judgment</l>
                  <l>Then Ingenuity.— Madam, let me be</l>
                  <l>The happy Meſſenger of this good news.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleanth.</speaker>
                  <l>Poor <hi>Cleantha!</hi> poor <hi>Endymion!</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Aſide.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pri.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleanth.</speaker>
                  <l>Enough Sir.—I am not aſham'd</l>
                  <l>My Prieſt ſhould know, what my Prayers are not</l>
                  <l>Aſham'd to own.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pri.</speaker>
                  <l>Then you love <hi>Endymion.</hi>—</l>
                  <l>Confeſs it, if you're not aſham'd.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleanth.</speaker>
                  <l>It may be</l>
                  <l>It ſuits not with my Modeſty to ſay ſo:</l>
                  <l>Nor yet with my Religion to deny it.—</l>
                  <l>I am ſorry you are angry, Sir.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pri.</speaker>
                  <l>Ah! dear Princeſſe,</l>
                  <l>I am not angry; that would not become me.</l>
                  <l>I am afflicted, Madam, I am afflicted,</l>
                  <l>At what much leſs becomes your Highneſs.— Can</l>
                  <l>You love ſo mean a Lord, and own it too,</l>
                  <l>And ſtill think your ſelf innocent, and talk</l>
                  <l>Of Modeſty, and ſay Love is no ſin?</l>
                  <l>And pray—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleanth.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, Sir, I muſt be bold, when you</l>
                  <l>Inſtruct me to be ſo, and interrupt</l>
                  <l>That Language, Sir, you muſt not let me hear.</l>
                  <l>Know, I may love <hi>Endymion,</hi> and yet talk</l>
                  <l>Of Innocence and Modeſty, much more then you</l>
                  <l>May of Civility, when you preſume, Sir,</l>
                  <l>To tell me, to my face, the contrary.—</l>
                  <l>You'll pardon me, I hope, Sir.— I would fain</l>
                  <l>Remember you, yet not forget my ſelf.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pri.</speaker>
                  <l>Pardom my paſſion, Madam.— 'Tis for you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clean.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis not for me to hear.—That Modeſty</l>
                  <l>You dar'd to doubt (heaven, have I heard it!)—Know,</l>
                  <stage>She cryes.</stage>
                  <l>Is much too tender to be touch'd, Sir, with</l>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:54200:22"/>
                  <l>Hard fingers yet.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prieſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Dear Princeſſe pardon me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clean.</speaker>
                  <l>Had you not been my Prieſt, I could have thought</l>
                  <l>So bold a paſſion: but for you, who teach,</l>
                  <l>That all the Wealth and Grandeur in the world</l>
                  <l>Doth hold no more proportion with true Vertue,</l>
                  <l>Then this world with Elyſium, her reward:</l>
                  <l>For you who teach this, and have taught it me,</l>
                  <l>(And if you teach it not, your Function's nothing)</l>
                  <l>For you (I ſay) to be ſo much in paſſion,</l>
                  <l>I love <hi>Endymion,</hi> who is poor, but hath</l>
                  <l>More vertue then a thouſand Princes: this</l>
                  <l>Is wonder, Sir: But for your office ſake,</l>
                  <l>I'll think you ſpeak not your own words; and ſo</l>
                  <l>I ſtill may reverence you; as you well know</l>
                  <l>I ſtill have done.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prieſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, have I your pardon?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleanth.</speaker>
                  <l>You have it, Sir.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prieſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Then give me leave to be</l>
                  <l>Gratefull, and ſerve you. Humbly to diſcuſſe</l>
                  <l>This Love you're pleas'd to own, without the leaſt</l>
                  <l>Of prejudice, or favour. Thus you may</l>
                  <l>Beſt judge of this great action of your life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleanth.</speaker>
                  <l>You have it, Sir; and may oblige me with it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prieſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Then know, faire—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clean.</speaker>
                  <l>But when you name <hi>Endymion.</hi>—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prieſt.</speaker>
                  <l>— Your pleaſure, Madam.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clean.</speaker>
                  <l>— Nothing.— I do attend you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prieſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, Madam, pray be free.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clean.</speaker>
                  <l>It's nothing, Sir.—</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Endymion</hi> needs not my Apology.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prieſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, you do acknowledge that you love</l>
                  <l>The Lord <hi>Endymion?</hi>—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleanth.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, I do to you,</l>
                  <l>But never have to him; and it may be</l>
                  <l>I never will.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prieſt.</speaker>
                  <l>(Your Highneſſe doth oblige me)—</l>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:54200:22"/>
                  <l>And you do ſeem to give this reaſon, 'cauſe</l>
                  <l>He ownes more vertue then a thouſand Princes;</l>
                  <l>Which, ſure, is probable. Yet, Madam, know,</l>
                  <l>That there are Princes too are vertuous</l>
                  <l>As he: and in particular, the high-</l>
                  <l>Born Prince of <hi>Macedon,</hi> who courts your Highneſſe,</l>
                  <l>Doth yield to none, but hath as good a title</l>
                  <l>To Virtue as his Crown.— Now, though you ought</l>
                  <l>To prefer Vertue before Wealth, or Greatneſſe,</l>
                  <l>As what is of more value then them both;</l>
                  <l>Yet theſe are both fair Pedals unto Vertue;</l>
                  <l>They much advance her ſtature, and do make</l>
                  <l>Her more conſpicuous to the world, and ſo</l>
                  <l>Much more ador'd; and therefore alwayes are</l>
                  <l>To be preferr'd, when to be had with her.</l>
                  <l>Low Violets may ſmell among the graſſe</l>
                  <l>And their own leaves, whilſt that the nobler Roſe</l>
                  <l>Adornes the Garden, and is no leſſe ſweet.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clean.</speaker>
                  <l>Sweeter then both in your compariſon.—</l>
                  <l>But, Sir, if it be poſſible t'advance</l>
                  <l>This humble Violet almoſt unto</l>
                  <l>The ſtature of the Roſe, to whom great Nature</l>
                  <l>Hath gi'n a higher ſtem, though not more ſweetneſs;</l>
                  <l>Pray, would it not be more of charity</l>
                  <l>And judgement, then t' endeavour with more hazard,</l>
                  <l>To adde ſome leaves unto that Roſe, whom Nature</l>
                  <l>Already had made fair enough?—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pri.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam,</l>
                  <l>I well do underſtand, your Highneſſe owns</l>
                  <l>Greatneſs enough to make another Great:</l>
                  <l>And that the Prince of <hi>Macedon</hi> appears</l>
                  <l>Already fair enough to all the world:</l>
                  <l>Yet ſurely, Madam, though your ſtructure be</l>
                  <l>Noble and high, if you will build it on</l>
                  <l>A low foundation, it can ne'er appeare</l>
                  <l>So high, as if your Baſis higher were.</l>
                  <l>You may appear your ſelf; but when you do</l>
                  <l>Joyn with an equall, you appear him too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clean.</speaker>
                  <l>Pardon me, Sir, I onely him appear.</l>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:54200:23"/>
                  <l>I loſe my name, and all I was before.</l>
                  <l>I am not greater (when his wife) becauſe</l>
                  <l>I was a Princeſſe; for ſhould he but wed</l>
                  <l>The meanſt Laſs in all <hi>Arcadia,</hi> he</l>
                  <l>In doing ſo, would make her full as great</l>
                  <l>As I ſhould be. Ambitious Rivers, whilſt</l>
                  <l>They needs will ſtrive to joyn with greater Floods,</l>
                  <l>Do adde indeed to them, but loſe themſelves,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt thoſe that court ſome ſmaller Brook at once,</l>
                  <l>Encreaſe their Waters, and preſerve their Names.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pri.</speaker>
                  <l>M<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dam, you will do well to heed, that whilſt</l>
                  <l>You ſeek t'encreaſe your Waters, you do not</l>
                  <l>Encreaſe your Years too. Mighty Floods, you know</l>
                  <l>Glide ſmooth, yet bear down all; whilſt little Brooks</l>
                  <l>Murmure at Pebles in their way, and have</l>
                  <l>Their courſes oft obſtructed. And, Madam, what,</l>
                  <l>What is a Name to the unfortunate?</l>
                  <l>What is a Name to thoſe, whoſe Names muſt live</l>
                  <l>But in their Epitaph? if you do wed</l>
                  <l>A Prince, the faire <hi>Cleantha</hi> will adorn</l>
                  <l>His Chronicle, and that in recompence,</l>
                  <l>Will make that Name immortall as her Merit.</l>
                  <l>But if you will in common Chanels run,</l>
                  <l>Poor neighbour-Towns may know your Name, but Mapps</l>
                  <l>Will heed you not. And then the brave <hi>Cleantha</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Will ſet with her own face; and th' injut'd world</l>
                  <l>Shall loſe her beſt Example, to thoſe Ages</l>
                  <l>Are yet to come; and thus <hi>Cleantha</hi> will</l>
                  <l>Undoe her ſelf, and all Poſterity.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleanth.</speaker>
                  <l>You almoſt do undoe my reaſon with</l>
                  <l>Your language, Sir.— But you well know, Sir, ſhould</l>
                  <l>I by each action of my life endeavour</l>
                  <l>To be forgotten in all Chronicle,</l>
                  <l>And leave it in my Will, to have my Name</l>
                  <l>Ne'er mention'd more; this very Will of mine</l>
                  <l>Would live to all Poſterity. Comets</l>
                  <l>As ſoon may unobſerved paſs among</l>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:54200:23"/>
                  <l>Aſtrologers, as any Princeſs can</l>
                  <l>Among Hiſtorians.— But, alas, Sir, what,</l>
                  <l>What's my Remembrance, when I am dead,</l>
                  <l>To be compar'd to the Contents of Life?</l>
                  <l>Shall I be wretched all the day, becauſe</l>
                  <l>I'd have folks talk of me when I'm aſleep?</l>
                  <l>What is it, if it be hereafter ſaid,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cleantha</hi> was the Queen of <hi>Macedon,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>When poor <hi>Cleantha</hi>'s but a little earth?</l>
                  <l>If I love nothing but <hi>Endymion,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nothing but him can make me happy, Sir;</l>
                  <l>And if I love nothing in him but his Vertue,</l>
                  <l>And his brave Soul, and can be well content</l>
                  <l>To loſe a Crown, and Title of a Queen,</l>
                  <l>To ſind thoſe better treaſures, though I ſtoop</l>
                  <l>To take them up, 't will be more glory, and</l>
                  <l>Eternity unto my Name, then if</l>
                  <l>(Like petty Countrey folks) I do diſpenſe</l>
                  <l>With Love for my convenience, and wed</l>
                  <l>What I may chance to like in time, with help</l>
                  <l>Of ſome good Counſel, and Neceſſity.—</l>
                  <l>This, Sir, will be an act, will give my Name</l>
                  <l>An honourable mention in the mouthes</l>
                  <l>Of Prieſts, and holy folks, as oft as they</l>
                  <l>Inſtruct men, that the Gods ſometimes reward</l>
                  <l>Vertue in this world, or that Vertue is</l>
                  <l>To be preferr'd before a Crown or Scepter.</l>
                  <l>For then it will be ſaid, <hi>Endymion</hi>'s vertue</l>
                  <l>Won him a Princeſs, and <hi>Cleantha</hi> did</l>
                  <l>Eſteem a brave <hi>Endymion</hi> much above</l>
                  <l>A Prince and Diadem. And thus my Greatneſs,</l>
                  <l>At once, ſhall make it ſelf more great, and ſerve</l>
                  <l>T' embalm the braveſt perſon in the world,</l>
                  <l>And make him, like my ſelf, immortal too.</l>
                  <l>For whiſt men write <hi>Cleantha</hi>'s Story, ſince</l>
                  <l>(Like her) it will be nought without <hi>Endymion,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The brave <hi>Endymion</hi> muſt be mentioned too,</l>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:54200:24"/>
                  <l>(That elſe perchance might have been numbred 'monſtg</l>
                  <l>Thoſe precious things, whoſe loſs the world bewails.)</l>
                  <l>And thus I ſhall oblige Poſterity,</l>
                  <l>More in <hi>Endymion</hi> then my ſelf: and ſhall</l>
                  <l>Give (like a Goddeſs) immortality,</l>
                  <l>To what was mortall in it ſelf, and had</l>
                  <l>Dy'd but for me.— This, Sir, I onely ſay,</l>
                  <l>To anſwer your objection; and I name</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Endymion,</hi> 'cauſe you nam'd him, as I did</l>
                  <l>The Roſe and Violet, when you were pleas'd</l>
                  <l>To inſtance in them.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prieſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Heaven! would it were but ſo.—</l>
                  <l>Madam, as errour ne'er can be more happy</l>
                  <l>Then in your mouth, nor more ſecure, who give</l>
                  <l>It ſo much beauty with your language, and</l>
                  <l>Strength with your Wit; ſo, can it never be</l>
                  <l>More dangerous.— And therefore, pardon me,</l>
                  <l>If I no longer do occaſion you</l>
                  <l>To ſhew th' omnipotency of your wit,</l>
                  <l>In (almoſt) making Errour, Truth; and tell you</l>
                  <l>What's ſurely true.— Madam, I have not thus</l>
                  <l>Preſum'd to interrupt this your Retirement</l>
                  <l>I found you in, on any confidence</l>
                  <l>Meerly my own, but onely in obedience</l>
                  <l>Unto the King's Command, your Royall Unkle,</l>
                  <l>Who underſtands (howe'er you little think it)</l>
                  <l>You love <hi>Endymion</hi> (Heaven would not conceall</l>
                  <l>So great an ill from him who may prevent it)</l>
                  <l>And hath commanded me to uſe my beſt</l>
                  <l>Endeavours to diſſwade you from an action</l>
                  <l>So much beneath your ſelf, and contrary</l>
                  <l>To his deſires, who with ſo dear affection</l>
                  <l>Hath ever treated you: And now refus'd</l>
                  <l>To ſpeak to you himſelf, leſt that his paſſion</l>
                  <l>Should move too violent 'gainſt what he hates,</l>
                  <l>And diſoblige what he ſo dearly loves.</l>
                  <l>To this ſo true and tender a regard<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:54200:24"/>
                  <l>Of this your Royal Unkle, Madam, what</l>
                  <l>Regardfull anſwer will you now command</l>
                  <l>Me to return him?—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>She reſts a while.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clean.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, I cannot tell</l>
                  <l>What way the King ſhould know what you affirm,</l>
                  <l>Since I ne'er ſaid ſo much to any perſon.—</l>
                  <l>I dare not think you would betray me, Sir.—</l>
                  <l>That were profane.— But if you muſt indeed,</l>
                  <l>Return ſome anſwer to the King, be pleas'd</l>
                  <l>To tell him, As I ever yet have been</l>
                  <l>Obedient to him, as my Unkle, ſo</l>
                  <l>I ſtill do think my ſelf oblig'd to be;</l>
                  <l>Suppoſing (as he hath not hitherto)</l>
                  <l>His Goodneſs never will command, cut what</l>
                  <l>Shall be within my power t' obey him in.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pri.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, this anſwer hath much Latitude.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clean.</speaker>
                  <l>It promiſeth, Sir, all I can.— You will not</l>
                  <l>Have me to promiſe more, I hope.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prieſt.</speaker>
                  <l>But is it</l>
                  <l>In your Highneſs power to love the Prince</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Macedon,</hi> and not to love <hi>Endymion?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clean.</speaker>
                  <l>I think, Sir, Love's as much within my power,</l>
                  <l>As't is in any other body's.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pri.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam,</l>
                  <l>I muſt intreat your Highneſs for an anſwer,</l>
                  <l>A little more direct unto the queſtion.—</l>
                  <l>You'l pardon me, I hope; I'm to deliver</l>
                  <l>It to a King.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clean.</speaker>
                  <l>And to receive it from</l>
                  <l>A Princeſſe, and a Maid.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pri.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, I ſhall</l>
                  <l>Be loath to tell the King you love the Lord</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Endymion.</hi>— And, may be, you'll be ſorry</l>
                  <l>To ſee him baniſht to ſome diſtant Iſle,</l>
                  <l>There to bewail his own perfections, that</l>
                  <l>He 'th pleas'd too much; and wiſh a thouſand times</l>
                  <l>You had not thus undone him with your love.—</l>
                  <l>Injure not, Madam, thus a Lord, who elſe</l>
                  <l>May number many happy daies, and live</l>
                  <l>An honour to his Countrey, and grow old,</l>
                  <l>And die among his Kindred, and his Friends.—</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:54200:25"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clean.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, this would be ſtrange juſtice, that my Love</l>
                  <l>Should be <hi>Endymion</hi>'s Crime.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prieſt.</speaker>
                  <l>'Twill prove ſo, Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clean.</speaker>
                  <l>He may be ſufferer, but not criminall.</l>
                  <l>And Heaven will do juſtice, when men do not.—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>She being ready to cry, fetcheth a ſigh, and goes as towards her ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pri.</speaker>
                  <l>Your humble ſervant, Madam.—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Ex. Prieſt. Cleantha perceiving the Prieſt gone, giveth way to her tears, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains ſtill ſpeaking thus to her ſelfe.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clean.</speaker>
                  <l>— Wretched <hi>Cleantha!</hi> Is thy Love a Crime?</l>
                  <l>A crime to him thou lov'ſt? Muſt it be ruine</l>
                  <l>Unto a perſon, if thou but affect'ſt him?</l>
                  <l>Have I ſome plague, that I muſt thus deſtroy</l>
                  <l>Whom I embrace? Or is my deſtiny</l>
                  <l>Grown paradoxicall, and proves my Love</l>
                  <l>To be true hatred? Or doth Heaven revenge</l>
                  <l>Other folk Pride, and my Humility?—</l>
                  <l>Oh Death, Death, Death! thou art not half ſo cruel</l>
                  <l>In thy deſtructions of the proſperous,</l>
                  <l>As in not killing wretches that would die?—</l>
                  <stage>She weeps.</stage>
                  <l>'Tis thou canſt make <hi>Cleantha</hi> happy; and</l>
                  <l>Preſerve <hi>Endymion</hi> ſo.—'Tis onely thy</l>
                  <l>Long night, and thy dark bed, that can give reſt</l>
                  <l>And ſleep to ſad <hi>Cleantha.</hi>—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Endymion.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>—<hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Hath not done well to treat me thus:— Alas,</l>
                  <l>Could I divine the Kings command? or durſt</l>
                  <l>I not obey him, or refuſe employment,</l>
                  <l>In which was Honour and Obedience too,</l>
                  <l>Unto my Prince, and Service to my Countrey?—</l>
                  <l>I took no leave of her; but I have told her</l>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:54200:25"/>
                  <l>The reaſons why my Love forbad it me.—</l>
                  <l>Surely <hi>Urania</hi>'s cruel.—She ought not ſure</l>
                  <l>To be thus angry, and accuſe me of</l>
                  <l>Slighting a poor deluded Shepherdeſs,</l>
                  <l>When I have vow'd ſo oft to her my love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clean.</speaker>
                  <l>Here comes my poor <hi>Endymion.</hi>—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>— The Princeſs!</l>
                  <l>She is ſtill gracious to me, and I were</l>
                  <l>Beſt to intreat her to perſwade my now</l>
                  <l>Provok'd <hi>Urania.</hi>— But ſhe's alone.—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>She ſteps aſide a little.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clean.</speaker>
                  <l>— Good morrow, my Lord.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>Your pardon, Madam, if unthought of, I</l>
                  <l>Have ruſht on your Retirement.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleanth.</speaker>
                  <l>Your preſence, Sir,</l>
                  <l>Will better it.— Pray what's the news from <hi>Argos?</hi>—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, the report was laſt night brought to Court,</l>
                  <l>Had nothing in't of truth. I found all quiet,</l>
                  <l>But onely for th' diſturbance that we made</l>
                  <l>Our ſelves, by our arrival in the night.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clean.</speaker>
                  <l>I'm glad, my Lord, your danger was no more.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>You do oblige me, Madam, to undergo</l>
                  <l>Much greater danger for your Highneſs, then</l>
                  <l>This could have prov'd.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clean.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, you have already</l>
                  <l>Purchas'd the name of my preſerver with</l>
                  <l>Your blood.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>'Twas at too cheap a rate.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clean.</speaker>
                  <l>Indeed</l>
                  <l>You ne'er can be in greater danger.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam,</l>
                  <l>The cauſe I fought for, made the danger nothing.</l>
                  <l>They might have kill'd me, but I could not die.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clean.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Nature's to oblige, my Lord.— I ſhall</l>
                  <l>Be happy, when I find it in my power</l>
                  <l>To let your Lordſhip know the great reſpect</l>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:54200:26"/>
                  <l>I have for that great Vertue which you own.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, 't hath been your Highneſs pleaſure ſtill</l>
                  <l>To honour with too great reſpect the little</l>
                  <l>Merits of your mean ſervant, who's advanc'd,</l>
                  <l>When numbred in the loweſt rank of thoſe</l>
                  <l>That have been fortunate to do you ſervice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clean.</speaker>
                  <l>You adde ſtill to my debts, my Lord, yet are</l>
                  <l>No wiſe injurious, ſince you make me rich,</l>
                  <l>In having ſuch a noble Creditor.—</l>
                  <l>But pray, my Lord, tell me (as one concern'd</l>
                  <l>Mach in your Fortunes, who have ſo oblig'd me)</l>
                  <l>(If it be fit for me to know, and you</l>
                  <l>Conceive, that by my wiſhes, or endeavours,</l>
                  <l>I any wiſe may ſtead you) what's the cauſe</l>
                  <l>Your Lordſhip hath not worn of late that reſt</l>
                  <l>Upon your looks, which heretofore appear'd</l>
                  <l>A happy witneſs to the world, you were</l>
                  <l>A world unto your ſelf, ſtill, and with wiſe</l>
                  <l>Content, bleſt all your fortunes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>Ah! great Princeſs;</l>
                  <l>It is for you to wear that Reſt, who are</l>
                  <l>Plac'd in that upper Region, where there is</l>
                  <l>No wind. But for a little Bark i'th' midſt</l>
                  <l>Of a great Sea, ſubject to every wave,</l>
                  <l>And all the winds, ſhe never muſt pretend</l>
                  <l>To this bleſt ſtate.— And for my troubles, Midam,</l>
                  <l>Alas, their objects will appear ſo ſmall</l>
                  <l>To your great Eye, you'd think I did affront you,</l>
                  <l>Should I dare ſay them to you.— Should the Lion in</l>
                  <l>His midnight walks for prey, hear ſome poor worms</l>
                  <l>Complain, for want of little drops of dew;</l>
                  <l>What pity could that generous creature have,</l>
                  <l>(who never wanted ſmall things) for thoſe poor</l>
                  <l>Ambitions? yet theſe are their concernments.</l>
                  <l>And but for want of theſe, they pine, and die.—</l>
                  <l>There muſt be ſome proportion ſtill to pity,</l>
                  <l>Between our ſelves, and what we moan: 'tis hard</l>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:54200:26"/>
                  <l>For men to be ought ſenſible, how Moats</l>
                  <l>Preſs Flies to death. Your Highneſs oft in jeſt,</l>
                  <l>Hath play'd away, more then ſome poor men have</l>
                  <l>Wrought all their life for.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleanth.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, I cannot tell,</l>
                  <l>Whether, poſſibly, what is your trouble, may</l>
                  <l>Not be augmented, by my knowing it.—</l>
                  <l>Elſe, ſhall I never think ought ſmall, that can</l>
                  <l>So much affect you, nor beneath my care,</l>
                  <l>To ſeek to remedy that gives you pain.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>Great Princeſs, you undo me with your Honours.</l>
                  <l>My blood turns all to bluſhes, as a ſham'd</l>
                  <l>It had not all been ſhed for your ſake, when</l>
                  <l>I had the honour to pour forth a little,</l>
                  <l>A ſacrifice to your great merits.— Madam,</l>
                  <l>I muſt obey your Highneſſes Command:</l>
                  <l>And thank you for it too; ſince in your knowledge</l>
                  <l>Of what afflicts me, is my remedy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleanth.</speaker>
                  <l>What will he tell me? Heaven! he knows I love him.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Aſide.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, I long have lov'd.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clean.</speaker>
                  <l>Whom, Sir?—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>The faire</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Urania,</hi> who attends your Highneſs.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clean.</speaker>
                  <l>Forgive,
<stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Forgive me, poor <hi>Endymion.</hi>—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>And have us'd</l>
                  <l>A thouſand arts to get her love, and had</l>
                  <l>Won her conſent, laſt night, to be my wife,</l>
                  <l>(Not doubting, Madam, but your Highneſs would</l>
                  <l>Have favoured me in this adventure) but</l>
                  <l>My ſudden being ſent to <hi>Argos,</hi> did</l>
                  <l>Unhappily abſolve this promiſe, and</l>
                  <l>I am accus'd by her for ſlighting of</l>
                  <l>An innocent Shepherdeſs, who was too forward</l>
                  <l>In truſting me, and in believing that</l>
                  <l>I e'er would match to one of her mean fortune.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:54200:27"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clean.</speaker>
                  <l>Indeed, my Lord, I never could have gueſs'd</l>
                  <l>Your melancholy had ſo mean a cauſe.</l>
                  <l>I could not think you would ſo far diſhonour</l>
                  <l>Your Family, and Name, as to have courted</l>
                  <l>So low a perſon.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, I well do know</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Urania</hi> was a Shepherdeſs, and born</l>
                  <l>In ſome low Cottage, 'mongſt thoſe little folks,</l>
                  <l>Whom Honour ſeldome viſits, and are bleſt</l>
                  <l>With nothing but their own content; but ſhe,</l>
                  <l>Like to a Star, miſtaken of his ſphere,</l>
                  <l>Grew ſo conſpucious 'mongſt thoſe dimmer lights,</l>
                  <l>That brave <hi>Theander</hi> had no ſooner ſpy'd her,</l>
                  <l>But he became all wonder, and would needs</l>
                  <l>Diſmiſs all but my ſelf, to talk with her.</l>
                  <l>I do remember yet, when firſt the Prince</l>
                  <l>Ask'd her ſome little queſtions, how (poor ſoul!)</l>
                  <l>She bluſht, and look'd upon her Lambs, as if</l>
                  <l>She'd have them take her part.— Her anſwers were</l>
                  <l>So innocent, as if ſhe'd been begot</l>
                  <l>By Prayer upon ſome Veſtal. This ſweet carriage,</l>
                  <l>From this ſweet perſon, caus'd the Prince almoſt,</l>
                  <l>For one whole Summer, ever when he hunted</l>
                  <l>About thoſe parts, to ſpend his pleaſant'ſt hours</l>
                  <l>With this fair Shepherdeſs; untill, at laſt,</l>
                  <l>He had perſwaded her (for ſhe was loath</l>
                  <l>To leave what ſhe well knew, for what ſhe knew not)</l>
                  <l>To leave her little flock, and go with him.</l>
                  <l>At what time he eſteem'd her fit to be</l>
                  <l>A P<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſent for your Highneſs, an Advancement</l>
                  <l>Few Families can boaſt of, ſince when (I know not</l>
                  <l>VVhether through your reflections on her, Madam,</l>
                  <l>VVho was celeſtiall, though obſcure before,</l>
                  <l>She did become a Star; or whether ſhe</l>
                  <l>Became a greater Imitator of</l>
                  <l>Your Highneſſes perfections, then all others)</l>
                  <l>She hath ſo added unto Nature, Art,</l>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:54200:27"/>
                  <l>That ſhe's grown bright to every eye; and Lords</l>
                  <l>And greateſt perſons of the Court are proud</l>
                  <l>To ſay <hi>Urania</hi> favours them to wear</l>
                  <l>The Title of her Servant, as a Gem</l>
                  <l>Too rich to be examin'd whence ſhe came.—</l>
                  <l>For her low Birth: Madam, this morning ſprung</l>
                  <l>Firſt to our eyes, from yonder barren hill;</l>
                  <l>And ſo will thouſand Stars at night, though this</l>
                  <l>And they, and ſhe are lights from Heaven all.</l>
                  <l>Their riſe is mean, or noble, only from</l>
                  <l>Our ſituation; ſo is hers: You caſt</l>
                  <l>Your eyes upon her, from the hight of Birth</l>
                  <l>And fortune too, and ſee her low; whilſt that</l>
                  <l>Some other Princeſs, Born as high, but not</l>
                  <l>Beneath ſo happy Stars, beholds her through</l>
                  <l>The thicker Medium of her Tears, and thinks</l>
                  <l>Her Birth more noble, 'cauſe more free and leſs</l>
                  <l>Subject to Fate, that doth like Thunder oft</l>
                  <l>O'erturn vaſt Oaks, whilſt <hi>Rue</hi> and <hi>Vervin</hi> ſtands.</l>
                  <l>Her Loves are free, (without which we may wear</l>
                  <l>Fetters of gold, but they are Fetters ſtill,</l>
                  <l>And fit as hard as Iron, though more rich)</l>
                  <l>Whilſt many great folks are conſtrain'd to wed</l>
                  <l>By Law and Policie, and marry thoſe</l>
                  <l>Old Men in Council ſhall think fit, who have</l>
                  <l>So many years for gotten love, and hate</l>
                  <l>Now all but wealth and Empire, 'cauſe themſelves</l>
                  <l>Have nothing elſe to boaſt of left—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Cleantha <hi>being not able longer to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain her ſelf at this, goes abruptly from</hi> Endym. <hi>to a Sun-Dial which ſtood not far from the walk, where ſhe lets fall ſome tears (her back be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing towards</hi> Endymion) <hi>and ſays with a low voice</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleantha!</speaker>
                  <l>Now thou art not fond. <hi>Endymion</hi> ſaith,</l>
                  <l>Thou art unhappy.—And wilt thou ſay ſo,</l>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:54200:28"/>
                  <l>And leave me ſo, <hi>Endymion?</hi> —No, my paſſion</l>
                  <l>Is now Authoriz'd, and I'll ſpeak.—</l>
                  <stage>She wipes her eyes.</stage>
                  <l>My Lord,</l>
                  <l>Would you think it were ſo late already?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Endym</hi> — Indeed</l>
                  <stage>Endym. Comes to the Dial.</stage>
                  <l>I cou'd not think it had been night ſo late.</l>
                  <l>But every part of Heaven haſts to ſee</l>
                  <l>What it ſo loves, and favours, your bright ſelf.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleant.</speaker>
                  <l>Well, my Lord, I do not wonder much</l>
                  <l>So great a Wit ſhould thus maintain ſo great</l>
                  <l>A Paradox; ſince that in nothing leſs</l>
                  <l>It can find its true exerciſe. — But ſay,</l>
                  <l>(And tell me truly) ſhould I make't my care</l>
                  <l>To chuſe a Miſtreſs for you, fair as <hi>Urania,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(If thouſands may be judges) and as Vertuous</l>
                  <l>(Becauſe ſhe truely honours Vertue) but</l>
                  <l>Extracted from a Family would give</l>
                  <l>Luſter to yours, although it were as mean</l>
                  <l>As hers you court now: ſay! would you not leave</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Urania</hi> for her, who doth ſeem to me</l>
                  <l>To undervaule your reſpects?—</l>
                  <l>Tell me, my Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>pauſeth a while.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Madam—ſhould your highneſs condeſcend to chuſe</l>
                  <l>A Torment for me, it were impudence</l>
                  <l>In me to chuſe ought elſe. But that's all bleſt</l>
                  <l>Which is ſo like <hi>Urania.</hi>—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleant.</speaker>
                  <l>So like to her?—</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi>'s body's fair, but what's that mind</l>
                  <l>Which cannot apprehend the true contents</l>
                  <l>Of being bound with ſacred chaynes to him,</l>
                  <l>Who in her Cloſet, and alone can be</l>
                  <l>The whole world to her, unto whom ſhe may</l>
                  <l>Bring all her doubts, and tell her ſorrows, and</l>
                  <l>Repeat her joyes, and have his cenſure on them?</l>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:54200:28"/>
                  <l>What is that minde which cannot value ſuch</l>
                  <l>True ſatisfactions more (perchance) then Crowns</l>
                  <l>And Sceptres? which is more then e'er <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Doth ever hope for ſure—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>Great Princeſs! could I own</l>
                  <l>Half thoſe perfections, <hi>I</hi> might happy be</l>
                  <l>Without <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania.</hi> — But <hi>Urania</hi> knows</l>
                  <l>She may find thouſands of more merit then</l>
                  <l>The poor <hi>Endymion,</hi> who durſt never meaſure</l>
                  <l>Himſelf, but by the paſſion he had for her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleant.</speaker>
                  <l>Sure, 'twas his modeſty. He might have thriven</l>
                  <l>Much better, poſſibly, had his ambition</l>
                  <l>Been greater much.</l>
                  <l>They oft-times take more payns,</l>
                  <l>Who look for Pins, then thoſe who finde out Stars.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>They do, and are unfortunate. But know,</l>
                  <l>Know higheſt Princeſs, thoſe may ſearch for ſuch</l>
                  <l>Small things you're pleas'd to name, who only have</l>
                  <l>A little candle of as ſmall a value:</l>
                  <l>But thoſe who ſeek out Stars, muſt be provided</l>
                  <l>VVith Arts and Glaſſes, and ſuch coſtly things</l>
                  <l>As humble folkes muſt be content to want.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleant.</speaker>
                  <l>Thoſe coyer Stars indeed, which ſo retire</l>
                  <l>Their little eyes in Heavens vaſt Boſom, do</l>
                  <l>(They ſay) require thoſe things you mention; but</l>
                  <l>For others of more magnitude, you need</l>
                  <l>Only to fix your eyes, and they'll appear</l>
                  <l>By their own light; and all you have to do,</l>
                  <l>Is to receive thoſe Beams they caſt upon you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>You cannot erre, great Princeſs—But 'tis hard</l>
                  <l>To fix our eyes aright upon that part</l>
                  <l>Of Heaven where thoſe Stars inhabit, if</l>
                  <l>VVe have not ſome directions firſt.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleant.</speaker>
                  <l>Indeed</l>
                  <l>Thoſe who look downwards ought to be directed</l>
                  <l>To look above them—to the higheſt ſphere—</l>
                  <l>(For there the Stars—are) then I'm apt to think</l>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:54200:29"/>
                  <l>Their task will not prove hard.—
<stage>She bluſheth.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>My Lord, I bluſh</l>
                  <l>Thus to inſtruct you in Aſtronomy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>No wonder, Madam, if I'm proud of what</l>
                  <l>You bluſh at, and eſteem this my beſt knowledge</l>
                  <l>VVhich your unbounded wit (perhaps) to morrow</l>
                  <l>Will with much greater reaſon quite deny.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clean.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, you think no woman's ever conſtant</l>
                  <l>To what ſhe ſaith, a day, but your <hi>Urania.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But till you've try'd, pray have more charity.</l>
                  <l>You'll after have more Faith.—'Tis late, my Lord:</l>
                  <l>You have oblig'd me with your company.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Clean.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym. ſol.</speaker>
                  <l>—VVhat meant this laſt diſcourſe?— Heaven!</l>
                  <l>bleſt Heaven!</l>
                  <l>VVas't not enough to loſe my dear <hi>Urania,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Unleſs I alſo did adore the hand</l>
                  <l>VVhich ſnatch'd her from me! <hi>Cleantha</hi> love <hi>Endymion!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The great, the pure <hi>Cleantha!</hi>— All my hopes</l>
                  <l>In rich and holy Incenſe ſtifled are.</l>
                  <l>The worlds beſt light hath burnt my Phenix with</l>
                  <l>A thouſand Spices — but Fool <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it cannot be.</l>
                  <l>Can brave <hi>Cleantha</hi> love the poor <hi>Endymion?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cleantha,</hi> pardon this wild thought, forgive</l>
                  <l>The proud <hi>Endymion.</hi> Never may he know</l>
                  <l>Thy noble breaſt harbour a thought ſo low.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Exit</hi> Endym</stage>
               <trailer>
                  <hi>Finis</hi> Act. 3.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:54200:29"/>
               <head>ACTUS 4.</head>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Neander <hi>ſol. in a fury.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <p>I Wonder who the Devil intends I ſhall marry with; for marry I will, by Heaven, though the Match be made in Hell. I have been a ſervant, as they call it, (that is, I have ſworn, and ly'd and ſpent money upon every Lady of Quality in the whole Court) yet I am ſtill ſo far from having a Wife among them all, as the veryeſt Eunuch in the Great Turks Seraglio is from having a Child among all thoſe wenches. Indeed, I never was in any probability (unleſs in my own conceit) of winning any one but the ſweet <hi>Evadne;</hi> and now, that the Queen, and her ugly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſhould croſs me, ſhould forbid her to ſpeak to me, to ſee me, it is what I cannot, I will not bear, though Fate it ſelfe ſay I ſhall do it. No, I have been told, that moſt old folks, when the Wine of Love is worn our in them, live ſome years by its Vinegar, Spight; and I will do the ſame, I am reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; and that old gray Prieſt and his Miſtreſs, the Queen, ſhall be my ſubjects. And yet, I am not ambitious to ſhew my valour ſo far, as to be hang'd for it neither. This (if I can do it) ſhall be the ſweeteſt part of my revenge, That I will live, and tread, and ſpit upon their Graves.</p>
                  <p>— But who comes here? <hi>Geron?</hi> A Rogue for my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, it may be. Here is a fellow now that will be glad to be hang'd, on any terms in the world, that hath been more plagu'd with one Wife, then I have been with all my Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes.—<hi>Geron,</hi> How is it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Geron.</speaker>
                  <p>How, is what, my Lord?— But let it be what it Will, I don't care three pence how it be.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <p>How, <hi>Geron!</hi> why ſo ſullen? I mean, how is it with you, Sir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <p>With me, my Lord? why juſt as folks ſay it is with
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:54200:30"/>the Devil: I goe up and downe, and carry my Hell with me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nean.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſay you to a bottle of wine in my chamber, <hi>Geron,</hi> to quench it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <p>As much to that as to any thing elſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nean.</speaker>
                  <p>Come along, then.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Ex. Nean. Geron.</stage>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Endymion, <hi>with his hands bound, attended by a Guard of Souldiers.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>— VVhy, may I not ſee the Princeſs,</l>
                  <l>For whom I'm baniſhed, before I go?—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Offic.</speaker>
                  <p>No, no, along.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Pray Sir walk a little faſter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Prethee let the Gentleman alone. Soft and fair goeth farre; and the Gentleman conſiders he hath farre to goe.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Endym. <hi>caſts his eyes towards</hi> Clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha<hi>'s apartment.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>Farewell then brave <hi>Cleantha;</hi> maiſt thou never</l>
                  <l>Once think <hi>Endymion</hi> ſuffers for thy ſake.—</l>
                  <l>And farewell, dear <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania;</hi> I will love thee</l>
                  <l>On thoſe hard Rocks I now muſt dwell upon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Off.</speaker>
                  <p>VVhat's this muttering?— along.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2. <hi>Soul.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Good Gentleman; he's loath to leave the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, I'll warrant him.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1.</speaker>
                  <p>Here ſhe comes.—</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Cleantha, <hi>two Ladies following her.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clean.</speaker>
                  <l>—Unmoved,</l>
                  <l>As if he went to meet thoſe Triumphs which</l>
                  <l>His worth alone deſerves.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>— The Princeſs.—</l>
                  <l>—Great Princeſs pardon</l>
                  <stage>He takes off his hat with his two hands, as they are bound, and kneels to her.</stage>
                  <l>My glorious ſufferings. Forgive me, that</l>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:54200:30"/>
                  <l>I ever ſaw the light, or liv'd a minute,</l>
                  <l>That you are injur'd thus by him, whoſe being</l>
                  <l>'S not worth your meaneſt thought.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clean.</speaker>
                  <l>Ah, my <hi>Endymion!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>She lets fall ſome tears.</stage>
                  <l>Affront not poor <hi>Cleantha.</hi>—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Endymion <hi>ſtoops down to kiſs the bottom of her garment; which ſhe perceiving, gives him her hand, which he kiſſeth.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clean.</speaker>
                  <l>Riſe, brave <hi>Endymion,</hi> 'tis my misfortune,</l>
                  <l>Thou art too low already.—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>He riſeth.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>Fortune made</l>
                  <l>Me low, to be advanced by a hand</l>
                  <l>More worthy then her own.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clean.</speaker>
                  <l>My noble Lord,</l>
                  <l>I have undone thee. What can I give thee now</l>
                  <l>In recompence of Liberty, and all</l>
                  <l>The pleaſures of this life, which thou muſt loſe</l>
                  <l>In a ſad baniſhment for her, who onely</l>
                  <l>Can be afflicted at thy ſufferings?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, you have enough to give, to pay</l>
                  <l>So mean a debt (if you will call it one)</l>
                  <l>A thouſand times.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clean.</speaker>
                  <l>Name it, and take it, deare</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Endymion,</hi> though it be my life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam,</l>
                  <l>Then grant me this requeſt; uſe every Art,</l>
                  <l>To make your hours as bleſt, as (I ſhall pray)</l>
                  <l>They may be many. And never let a thought</l>
                  <l>E'er repreſent to your remembrance more</l>
                  <l>Unfortunate <hi>Endymion.</hi>—Then ſhall I ſee,</l>
                  <l>Among the Deſolations of my Fortune,</l>
                  <l>This cheerfull Green. The brave <hi>Cleantha</hi>'s happy.</l>
                  <l>She wears a Crown, and lives adore'd; what then,</l>
                  <l>Though poor <hi>Endymion</hi> ſuffer baniſhment,</l>
                  <l>Though he.—</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:54200:31"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Officers.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, this is what was forbidden us to permit you.</l>
                  <l>You muſt away Sir.—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Takes him by the arm.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleanth.</speaker>
                  <l>Impudent Villain, dar'ſt thou interrupt</l>
                  <l>A perſon <hi>I</hi> am talking with?—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Offic.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, Madam,</l>
                  <l>VVhen <hi>I</hi> have the Kings commands to do ſo.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>—Madam,</l>
                  <l>Theſe perſons do their duty: they are the hands</l>
                  <l>Of Fate that pull me from you.—Sacred Princeſs,</l>
                  <l>All that is bliſs attend you.—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>He kneels to kiſs her hand. She ſtoops, and kiſſeth him.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleant.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, farewel.—</l>
                  <l>Know that <hi>Cleantha</hi> loves thee, and will never</l>
                  <stage>She gives him a Ring.</stage>
                  <l>Be happy 'till <hi>Endymion</hi> make her ſo.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>I cannot doubt, but Heaven will proſper what</l>
                  <l>'S ſo like it ſelf. Bleſt Princeſs, take my Prayers:</l>
                  <l>Heaven thinks not fit t' intruſt me with ought elſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Cleant. with her attendants.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>ſol.</hi> Thus Fate directs me what <hi>I</hi> now muſt do</l>
                  <l>To ſerve my Shepherdeſs and Princeſs too.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Endymion</hi> Falls; but to the firſt he dies</l>
                  <l>A Lover, to the laſt a Sacrifice.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Exit</hi> Endym. <hi>and his guard.</hi>
               </stage>
               <stage>Enter Evadne, and to her Neander; at which ſhe ſeems troubled, and willing to haſte from him.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <l>My dear, and why ſo faſt?—What, haſt thou wounded</l>
                  <l>Thy poor <hi>Neander,</hi> and now fly'ſt him?—Your ſervant,</l>
                  <l>Faireſt <hi>Evadne.</hi>—Why this haſte —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Evad.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, you will</l>
                  <l>Oblige me much if you permit it; and</l>
                  <l>Be pleas'd to think there is a reaſon for it:</l>
                  <l>And ask it not.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <l>Muſt then <hi>Neander</hi> die,</l>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:54200:31"/>
                  <l>And never know his crime. Cruel <hi>Evadne,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Give me that eaſe in death, to let me know</l>
                  <l>How I've deſerv'd it.—Speak, my dear <hi>Evadne:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Tell me the reaſon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Evad.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, I'm but a childe,</l>
                  <l>And all my reaſon is obedience.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <l>Obedience to that Prieſt!—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Evad.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, he's my Father.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <l>Who more eſteems a heavie-headed fool</l>
                  <l>(Who's but afraid to ſwear, thinks moſt old women</l>
                  <l>Are Witches, and that dead-folks walk) although</l>
                  <l>Not worth a groat, then him who owns at once</l>
                  <l>A generous Fortune, with a generous Soul?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Evad.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, he's my Father; and who injures him,</l>
                  <l>Ne'er pleaſeth me. His part is to command.</l>
                  <l>Mine is obedience.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay <hi>Evadne,</hi> pray</l>
                  <l>Hear this before you go: 'twill be the fruit</l>
                  <l>Of your obedience, think ne'er of marying till</l>
                  <l>You ſee three caps, a narrow band, a mouth</l>
                  <l>Miſhap'd <hi>By my Truly,</hi> and the Cough—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Evadne.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neand.</speaker>
                  <p>I perceive you'll hear no more of your ſervant, Madam: adieu. — What ſimpleton in all <hi>Arcadia,</hi> but this Prieſt, would not have married his daughter to my eſtate, had I been the veryeſt coxcomb in <hi>Greece?</hi> Why, ſo he might but have ſaid his daughter My Lady ſuch a one, and talked of her Gentleman-uſhers, her Pages, and her women, who would ever have ſtood upon it whether her husband had been a Philoſopher, or (as they call it) an honeſt man? Poor <hi>Evadne,</hi> Thy Mother died too ſoon for thee; ſhe (good wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man) (I'll warrant her) would have made a hard ſhift to have ſate at the upper end of my Lord <hi>Neanders</hi> Table, to have had occaſion to make up a fine mouth, and ſaid, My ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to you Son <hi>Neander,</hi> before all the company: and then to have ſaid to <hi>Evadne,</hi> Daughter, you don't help my Lord. She (good woman) would have thought of theſe things—
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:54200:32"/>and he ſhall go to her to learn more wit ſhortly.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Evadne,</speaker>
                  <l>I am mad; but it cann't be,</l>
                  <l>Mad as I am, but I will marry thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Neand.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Cleantha and her Nource.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleant.</speaker>
                  <p>—Nource, where's <hi>Endymion</hi> now?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nource.</speaker>
                  <p>He's where he wants good company, I believe, poor Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleant.</speaker>
                  <l>Nource, ſay not ſo, becauſe his ſteadfaſt minde</l>
                  <l>Still leaves him with himſelf, and thus he'th ſtill</l>
                  <l>The beſt of company— My dear <hi>Endymion.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nource.</speaker>
                  <p>Come, come Madam, your Highneſs muſt ſtudy to forget him now, and think of ſome other bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleanth.</speaker>
                  <l>Forget him (fooliſh-woman!) I ſooner ſhall</l>
                  <l>Forget that I have eyes, forget I have</l>
                  <l>A memory. Shall brave <hi>Endymion</hi> dwell</l>
                  <l>In baniſhment for me, and I forget him?—</l>
                  <l>Sure thou wouldſt minde me of him, if I ſhould.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nource.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, Madam, I wiſh your Highneſs do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member him too much. I am glad you are alive yet, for my part; now he's gone.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleant.</speaker>
                  <l>Indeed, I ſpeak, and do the offices</l>
                  <l>Of life as yet. But ſay, ſay, my dear <hi>Nource,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Did'ſt never ſee a Tree cut down in ſpring,</l>
                  <l>A while put forth his buds and leaves, as if</l>
                  <l>He'd been a live, until that ſap was ſpent</l>
                  <l>Which he had ſuck'd from his life-giving Root:</l>
                  <l>And then he wither'd?—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter King and Queen.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <p>How do you Neece?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                  <p>VVe are come to viſit you in the abſence of your Lover.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleant.</speaker>
                  <p>Your Majeſties do always do me honour.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed Neece, you ought to thank thoſe who do
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:54200:32"/>you honour, when you forget to do it to your ſelf.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cleantha,</hi> you are not too much diſcontented (I hope) at <hi>Endymions</hi> departure. You are too wiſe to be ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleant.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, whatever my troubles are, as they are my own, ſo I ſhall endeavour not to make them any other bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <p>Neece, you ought to look to the juſtice of the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſo be ſatisfied.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleant.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed, there's little of mercy in it to be ſeen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <p>VVell Neece, I ſhall not diſpute the buſineſs over with you again. The Prieſt, the Queen, and my ſelf have done it already at large, and you ſeem to be reſolved not to be ſatisfied with any thing but your own unreaſonable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires. The action I have done is juſt, I thought it ſo, and I have done it, and will continue it, and you muſt be patient.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleant.</speaker>
                  <p>Your Majeſty may pleaſe to know, that I ſhall have ſo much regard to my ſelf, as not to permit my impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience to be troubleſome to other folks.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit King.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                  <l>Come <hi>Cleantha,</hi> prethee be not ſad.</l>
                  <l>The Prince of <hi>Macedon</hi> will make a better</l>
                  <l>Husband then <hi>Endymion.</hi>—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleant.</speaker>
                  <l>It may be ſo.</l>
                  <l>And ſome one elſe will make a better wife</l>
                  <l>For him then I ſhall do.—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Phroneſ.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                  <p>VVhat newes with you, <hi>Phroneſia?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phroneſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Only a word or two, that doth a little Import your Majeſty to know.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Queen</speaker>
                  <l>I'm going, wench.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cleantha,</hi> fare you well. I hope I ſhall</l>
                  <l>Next finde your Melancholy leſs—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt Queen and Phroneſ.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleant.</speaker>
                  <l>—VVhy ſhould they call it melancholy, Nource?</l>
                  <l>Love is not melancholy; this is cold,</l>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:54200:33"/>
                  <l>But that a burning flame; this dry, and that</l>
                  <l>All tears.—But why this wonder?—I sit ſtrange that ſuch</l>
                  <l>Are ignorant of Love, who never knew it?</l>
                  <l>VVho wedded are indeed, but not becauſe</l>
                  <l>Their ſouls were equal, but their fortunes; not</l>
                  <l>That they themſelves, but Parents did agree.—</l>
                  <l>And think they that <hi>Cleantha</hi>'ll do ſo too?</l>
                  <l>Is ſhe ſo ſmall a needy Girl, to chuſe</l>
                  <l>A ſervant for advantage, and to love him</l>
                  <l>Until next our Commiſſioners diſagree,</l>
                  <l>And then to be indifferent again;</l>
                  <l>And never give account of her affections</l>
                  <l>Till ſhe've enquir'd firſt how the Chaffer goes?—</l>
                  <l>No, my dear Nource, I better underſtand</l>
                  <l>My preſent freedom, that true Monarchy</l>
                  <l>I'm to my ſelf, then on indifferent Parly</l>
                  <l>To yeeld my ſelf a cowardly Captive.—If</l>
                  <l>I fall, 't ſhall be by ſtorm; nor will I be</l>
                  <l>Conquer'd by ought leſs then a Deity.</l>
                  <l>To add unto thy triumphs, Love,'s no more</l>
                  <l>Then that which Goddeſſes have done before.</l>
                  <l>And this <hi>Cleantha</hi> may not bluſh to do,</l>
                  <l>Although a Princeſs, and a Virgin too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nource.</speaker>
                  <p>Madam, you are too wiſe; why ſhould you not contented be to do like all the world?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleant.</speaker>
                  <l>I ne'er examine, Nource, what moſt folks do,</l>
                  <l>But what all ſhould do, and thoſe few do practiſe,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe real Vertue never bluſh't to be</l>
                  <l>Brought to the teſt of reaſon. I can pardon</l>
                  <l>Poor ſilly Laſſes that believe their Granams,</l>
                  <l>Who tell them 'tis a ſin to intermix</l>
                  <l>With thoſe beneath them, (as though the rich and poor</l>
                  <l>Were different ſpecies) whoſe Sunburnt modeſties</l>
                  <l>Can well diſpence with th'loſs of that pure ſtate</l>
                  <l>Nature had plac'd them in, for the advantage</l>
                  <l>Of ſome convenient neighbourhood; but ſtill</l>
                  <l>I've no forgiveneſs for my ſelf, ſhould I</l>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:54200:33"/>
                  <l>(Grown now a woman, and endue'd with reaſon)</l>
                  <l>Play with thoſe Puppet-Vertues old folks give me,</l>
                  <l>And (underſtanding my own whiteneſs) ere</l>
                  <l>Diſſolve that Snow but by a flame as pure.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nource.</speaker>
                  <p>VVell, Madam, I cannot diſpute it with you. But ſure I am, I ſhould ne'er have got a husband on theſe Philoſophical tearms.—It is well for me I was not ſo wiſe at your age
<stage>[Cleant. ſmiles.]</stage> Why Madam, when I had loved any one (as that was no very hard matter for me to do when I was young) it had been ten to one if he had lov'd me again; and there I had been gone: Or if he had lov'd me, then his friends would not have liked it; and there I had been gone. Or if his friends had, then mine would have found ſome fault or other; and ſtill I had been gone.—Madam, there is ſo much to do, to bring two young folks together that have any thing in the world, that ſhould they refuſe marriage on any tearms, old maidens would be as plenty as Crabs are in <hi>America.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleant.</speaker>
                  <p>Prethee Nource no more.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nource.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, I was reſolv'd to put you out of your dump: you would have cry'd preſently, if I would have let you.— But, have you gi'en <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi> leave to be wanting?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleant.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, ſhe asked me to be a day or two with her Mother ſomewhere here in Town.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nource.</speaker>
                  <p>She look'd but ill when ſhe went: I thought ſhe had gone on ſome diſcontent.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleant.</speaker>
                  <p>I know none. She went hence two days ſince, I think.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nource.</speaker>
                  <p>Then ſhe ſhould be return'd again.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleant.</speaker>
                  <p>She may take her own time—Come, ſhall we go, Nource?—</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt Cleantha, and Nource.</stage>
               <stage>Enter the King and Pyrrhus.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>—Is't poſſible?—It cannot be—</l>
                  <l>My Queen,—My Queen an Adultereſs! and with</l>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:54200:34"/>
                  <l>My Prieſt too! Could Heaven not puniſh me</l>
                  <l>But by it's repreſentative? In what can men</l>
                  <l>Confide, if ſanctity and holy vows</l>
                  <l>Are nothing?—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>I am amaz'd.—The Queen</l>
                  <l>And Prieſt in womans Cloaths (ſtrange circumſtance!)</l>
                  <l>To meet i'th' Grotto now this night? ſure 'tis</l>
                  <l>Impoſſible!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>It muſt be ſo, unleſs</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Geron</hi> be quite mad, who's now ſecur'd,</l>
                  <l>And is content to die for't, if I ſee not</l>
                  <l>My ſelf, with my own eyes, all this, this night.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>Heaven bleſs me!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Ah my <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> Heaven is juſt;</l>
                  <l>'Tis we are wicked. In this very Grotto</l>
                  <l>I met <hi>Urania,</hi> and forgot my Queen;</l>
                  <l>Though then I thought her faithful, and almoſt</l>
                  <l>VVhite as Virginity itſelf.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis certain.—</l>
                  <l>But Heaven grant this metting prove no worſe</l>
                  <l>Then that did.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Bleſt Heaven grant it may not.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Majeſty may yet prevent it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>I may</l>
                  <l>For this time doubtleſs.— But I will not harbour</l>
                  <l>That Devil Jealouſie within my breaſt,</l>
                  <l>For all this world can give me. I'm reſolv'd</l>
                  <l>To ſee the certainly my ſelf. And if</l>
                  <l>It prove untrue, my Queen ſhall dwell with freedom</l>
                  <l>(As ſhe hath ever done) in all my thoughts,</l>
                  <l>And her accuſer fall her ſacrifice.</l>
                  <l>But if ſhe can forget her former Vertue,</l>
                  <l>I can forget my former Love, and be</l>
                  <l>As juſt as ſhe is wicked. I can take</l>
                  <l>As true a pleaſure then to ſee her blood</l>
                  <l>Drop from the fatal ſword, as ere I did</l>
                  <l>To ſee it bluſhing on her cheek when erſt</l>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:54200:34"/>
                  <l>I thought her modeſt.—And for the Prieſt, whom I</l>
                  <l>Have ever Father call'd, and have rever'd</l>
                  <l>More in my thoughts then language, if he can</l>
                  <l>Un-prieſt himſelf by wickedneſs, I can</l>
                  <l>Be glad to ſee thoſe hands in iron which</l>
                  <l>So oft have bleſt me; to behold him burn,</l>
                  <l>VVho hath burnt holy incenſe, and perfum'd</l>
                  <l>All my Devotions with it—I can glory</l>
                  <l>To let him feel this Truth, That 'tis Heaven's guiſe,</l>
                  <l>Not to have beaſts for Prieſts, but Sacrifice.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Queen and Prieſt.</stage>
                  <l>Look where they come.—Let us withdraw, it may be</l>
                  <l>VVe ſhall hear ſomething.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>Sure they ſee you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prieſt.</speaker>
                  <l>—And nothing is more common</l>
                  <l>Then this, which is not thought a ſin, becauſe</l>
                  <l>It ſeemeth rather an impulſe of Nature—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Hear'ſt thou, <hi>Pyrrhus!</hi>—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                  <l>The King—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Priest.</speaker>
                  <l>All happineſs attend your Majeſtie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt contain.— How doth my Queen?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                  <l>Always happy whilſt your Majeſty</l>
                  <l>Is ſo.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>And what are you diſcourſing?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                  <l>Nothing but good with this good perſon ſure.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>VVhat's that you talk of? that which is not ſin</l>
                  <l>'Cauſe an impulſe of Nature?—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Queen Smiles.</speaker>
                  <l>What means your Majeſty?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prieſt.</speaker>
                  <l>I know not how we came by chance to ſpeak</l>
                  <l>How little wantonneſs is thought a ſin</l>
                  <l>Becauſe it ſeemeth an impulſe of Nature;</l>
                  <l>VVhereas the Vertuous ſtill do fix their eye</l>
                  <l>On the Command, not the Temptation;</l>
                  <l>And think't enough, if what Heaven gives as Law</l>
                  <l>Be poſſible, although not natural.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King aſide.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis well put off.—I ſhall never hold</l>
                  <l>To hear this hypocrite.—Well, I muſt leave you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhall wait upon your Majeſty</l>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:54200:35"/>
                  <l>If't may not be a trouble.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>To you it may be.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Queen Smiles.</speaker>
                  <l>That as your Majeſty's pleaſure is to make it.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt King and Queen.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Priest.</speaker>
                  <l>How happy 'tis to ſee a King and Queen</l>
                  <l>Thus bleſtly live together?—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>Heaven keep them ſo.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prieſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray Heaven Amen.—My Lord, adieu.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Prieſt.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrhus ſolus.</speaker>
                  <l>Did I but dare to diſobey my Prince</l>
                  <l>In any thing, or call my ſelf to counſel</l>
                  <l>VVhether I ſhould reveal a ſecret he'th</l>
                  <l>Vouchſaf'd to tell me, I would certainly</l>
                  <l>Prevent this Tragedy. My Queen and Prieſt</l>
                  <l>Should ſtill be white and holy. But what Kings</l>
                  <l>Pleaſe to command, requires obedience, not</l>
                  <l>Examination: when they once have judg'd,</l>
                  <l>'Tis want of judgment if we dare judge too.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter King haſtily.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> I had forgot one thing. Thou knowſt the Prince is expected here to morrow, and I doubt he will be ſomewhat early too. It will be neceſſary his coming be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarded untill this buſineſs be over, that I may know with what face to receive him, after all the glorious actions he hath done. I would not for a world his arrival ſhould happen 'till the whole examination be over.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <p>It will be an unhappy entertainment for his Grace.—Would your Majeſtie pleaſe to have me go my ſelf?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <p>If thou canſt handſomely do it, and be early back in the morning. It is but riding all night. In the morning I ſhall want thee.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhall do it with much eaſe, if it be your Majeſties pleaſure.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:54200:35"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhall leave thee to frame the excuſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhall be gone immediately. Heaven grant I meet good newes to morrow morning.—</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Pyrrhus.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>I doubt that—</l>
                  <l>Thus we with them in plotting do conſent;</l>
                  <l>But they plot ſin, and we plot puniſhment.</l>
                  <l>And little think they in how ſmall a time</l>
                  <l>(Poor ſouls!) my juſtice ſhall o'ertake their crime.</l>
                  <l>Too happy were men, if they underſtood</l>
                  <l>There is no ſafety but in being good.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit King.</stage>
               <p>
                  <hi>Finis</hi> Act. 4.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <head>ACTUS 5.</head>
               <stage>Enter the King. He walks a while, then ſeateth himſelf in a Chayre.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>—UNfortunate <hi>Baſilius!</hi> How juſt</l>
                  <l>Are all thy puniſhments proportion'd, Heaven,</l>
                  <l>To unjuſt men! — Yet ſhould I dare to judge</l>
                  <l>Thoſe happy Eſſences that dwell in Light,</l>
                  <l>And cannot erre, I ſhould be apt to ſay,</l>
                  <l>My puniſhment exceeds my crime: my ſin</l>
                  <l>Went never farther then th' intention, and</l>
                  <l>My ſufferance is real.—But was't not</l>
                  <l>Solely your goodneſs that it reſted there?</l>
                  <l>And muſt you not be juſt now, 'cauſe you then</l>
                  <l>Were merciful?—</l>
                  <stage>Enter Pyrrh.</stage>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> undone—</l>
                  <l>My eyes are witneſſes. I ſaw them both</l>
                  <l>Enter the Grotto.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>The Prieſt in womans habit?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>King,</hi> All's true.—The Queen hath been already</l>
                  <l>Examin'd by the Councel.—All ſhe ſaith</l>
                  <l>Is, that ſhe's innocent; but will not ſay</l>
                  <l>The cauſe which mov'd her to an action ſo</l>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:54200:36"/>
                  <l>Suſpected, though ſhe die for't.—But ſuch, <hi>Fyrrhus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Are never innocent, who are aſham'd</l>
                  <l>To vindicate their deeds when once their lives</l>
                  <l>Do lie at ſtake for 't.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Majeſty was not preſent.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>No, I leave them totally to juſtice, I</l>
                  <l>Shall make the Law their judge.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>But pray</l>
                  <l>VVhat ſaith the Prieſt?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>I now expect to hear</l>
                  <l>Th' examination. It hath been very long,</l>
                  <l>Two houres at leaſt. It's bad enough, for certain.</l>
                  <l>But here it comes. My Lord, you have been long,</l>
                  <stage>Enter Lord of the Councel.</stage>
                  <l>But I expect no good, and therefore care not</l>
                  <l>If you had longer been.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
                  <l>An't pleaſe your Majeſty,</l>
                  <l>Before I can give ſatisfaction to</l>
                  <l>Your expectations, I muſt humbly pray</l>
                  <l>You will pleas'd to pardon the intreating</l>
                  <l>Your anſwer to a queſtion; on which all</l>
                  <l>That we have done depends.—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Pyrrhus withdraws a little.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>VVhat is it?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
                  <l>'T may ſeem too inſolent—but the whole truth</l>
                  <l>Of all th' examination wholly doth</l>
                  <l>Depend upon it, Whether your Majeſty</l>
                  <l>(For reaſons known beſt to your royal ſelf)</l>
                  <l>Did not one night command a little Lady</l>
                  <l>VVho waits upon the Princeſs, one <hi>Urania,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To attend you in that Grotto where</l>
                  <l>The Queen and Prieſt were ſeis'd on?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>I did.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
                  <l>And ſhe was there!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>She was.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
                  <l>And was your Majeſty</l>
                  <l>Aſſur'd that it was ſhe; or might it be</l>
                  <l>The Queen?—</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:54200:36"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Her whiſpers were the Queens: <hi>Pyrrhus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Knows what I told him.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>riſeth.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
                  <l>Be happy then great Prince—</l>
                  <l>Your Queen is Innocent, your Prieſt is holy,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Geron</hi> and <hi>Neader</hi> only are</l>
                  <l>The Criminals.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Relieve my wonder.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
                  <l>Hear,</l>
                  <l>Great Prince, in ſhort, a plot, that ſeems contriv'd</l>
                  <l>In Hell by Heaven, to add more whiteneſs to</l>
                  <l>The Vertuous.—Here is the Prieſts confeſſion.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Unrols a paper, and reads it.</stage>
               <stage>The confeſsion of the Prieſt, and his examination. With the confeſsion of Phroneſia, Geron and Neander.</stage>
               <p>That <hi>Geron</hi> came yeſterday in the afternoon unto the Prieſt; and after much ſeeming troubled, told him, that he had ſome houres before over-heard a contrivance between the Queen and the Lord <hi>Neander</hi> to meet at eleven of the clock that night at the Grotto in the Garden, and that <hi>Neader</hi> was to be habited like a woman, and the Queen to be dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed like a young laſs named <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi> who waits on the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, the better to prevent ſuſpition, in caſe they ſhould chance to be ſeen by any in their paſſage thither. This he aſſerted with much violence; and at laſt (after much diſcourſe) the Prieſt was perſwaded by him to attend the Queen there in the habit of a woman, inſtead of <hi>Neander</hi> (whoſe enterance he had promiſed to hinder, by ſhutting the door he was to paſs at to get into the garden) and thus, when the Queen ſhould begin to ſpeak to him as her Lover, he ſhould then make know himſelf unto her, and do his duty, in juſtly blam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her for ſo unvertuous an action.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <p>Where ends this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lordreads on.</speaker>
                  <p>This the Prieſt did. And he was not ſooner entred into the grotto, but he found the Queen there before him. But the Queen ſeeming to expect his ſpeaking firſt, and he not allowing his lips to be provided on this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:54200:37"/>told her plainly that ſhe was miſtaken of her Lover; that he was her Prieſt: and then producing a little light he had concealed in a dark Lanthorn, he manifeſted himſelf, and perfectly diſcerned the Queen, although in a diſguiſe. The Queen thinking her ſelf bound to give an account of her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there, and yet very loath to ſpeak the cauſe of it, at laſt told him, that as her Confeſſor, ſhe would reveal unto him, that the King had of late ſomewhat an immoderate reſpect for a young laſs named <hi>Urania</hi> belonging to the Princeſs, and that having forced a promiſe from the poor maid, ſhe did (by the Lord <hi>Endymions</hi> means) eaſily perſwade her ſelf (for the ſecuring of the Kings honour) to ſupply the place of the ſaid <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania,</hi> (they having agree'd to have no lights, and to ſpeak very low) which ſhe accordingly had done for ſome nights before, and with ſuch ſucceſs, that the King returned rather ſatisfied in his reaſon then his Love.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <p>All truth.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord reads on.</speaker>
                  <p>But having re-aſſumed his deſires, ſhe had again this night a ſummons to the ſame taske, from a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of hers nam'd <hi>Phroneſia;</hi> which was the occaſion of her being in that place. But all this ſhe did very paſſionately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the Prieſt to be ſecret in, in that it concerned ſo neerly the Kings honour.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <p>And what then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
                  <p>On this, we immediately ſent for <hi>Geron,</hi> who after many threats confeſs'd as followeth: That the Lord <hi>Neander</hi> being croſſed in his love to <hi>Evadne</hi> Daughter to the Prieſt, by the Queen, and Prieſt her Father, was reſolved on a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge for them both: and by removing them out of the way, to accompliſh his deſign of marrying <hi>Evadne.</hi> To this end, he promiſeth to <hi>Geron</hi> great rewards for the contrivance of the buſineſs, wo accidentally (by his ſculking up and down in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very corner to watch his wife <hi>Phroneſia,</hi> of whom he is very jealous) over-heard the agreement between <hi>Urania</hi> and <hi>Endymion,</hi> concerning the Queens ſupplying her place in the Grotto. On this foundation he founds the whole fabrick of his helliſh plot. For ſending his wife <hi>Phroneſia</hi> (who having been horribly abuſed by him, was willing notwithſtanding to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:54200:37"/>purchaſe his reſpect at any rate whatever) unto the Queen, as from <hi>Urania,</hi> only with theſe words in her mouth, That ſhe humbly deſired her Majeſty to think of her royal promiſe at eleven of the clock that night, and of the King, as ſhe had been pleaſed to do ſome few nights before: the Queen (he knew) would on this reſolve to be at that time in the Grotto. After which he goes himſelf to the Prieſt, and counts to him what is before repeated in the Prieſts confeſſion. And in the laſt place, he had the impudence to come to your Majeſty, and tell you what your Majeſty was pleaſed to inform us of. And all this <hi>Neander</hi> and he were reſolved to outface with oaths, in caſe it ſhould ever come to be examined (for they ſuppoſed it probable that your Majeſty would in fury have killed both the Queen and Prieſt on the place; which was the reaſon for which <hi>Geron</hi> perſwaded your Majeſty to have Piſtols or a Stilletto with you.)</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <p>Wicked Villains!—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
                  <p>After this, we ſent for <hi>Neander,</hi> who (amaz'd at his condition) confeſſed the whole buſineſs in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. As alſo <hi>Phroneſia,</hi> what <hi>Geron</hi> affirmed concerning her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Bleſt Heaven, how are thy wayes juſt like thy orbs,</l>
                  <l>Involv'd within each other? yet ſtill we finde</l>
                  <l>Thy judgments are like Comets, that do blaze,</l>
                  <l>Affright, but dye withall; whilſt that thy mercies</l>
                  <l>Are like the Stars, who oft-times are obſcured,</l>
                  <l>But ſtill remain the ſame behinde the clouds.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>May all your doubts and fears thus terminate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
                  <l>Thus are you ſhaken, to be more confirm'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> ſend for <hi>Urania;</hi> ſhe ſhall wear</l>
                  <l>This day the juſt rewards of Vertue. I</l>
                  <l>Will viſit my brave Queen, who rather choſe</l>
                  <l>To die unjuſtly as a Criminal,</l>
                  <l>Then that her Lord ſhould juſtly ſo be term'd.</l>
                  <l>For which I will proclaim my fault, ſince ſhe</l>
                  <l>Will have the glory of concealing it.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Pyrrhus.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
                  <l>Heaven bleſs your Majeſty.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord.</l>
                  <l>I'd have the Councel with all ſpeed remove</l>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:54200:38"/>
                  <l>Into the Hall, where before all the Court</l>
                  <l>I'll bring my Queen in triumph, there to hear</l>
                  <l>Her baſe accuſers ſentenc'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
                  <l>It ſhall be done</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt King and Lord.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Evadne weeping.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Evad.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas <hi>Evadne!</hi> miſerable Maid,</l>
                  <l>Why didſt thou ever begg to leave thy cell</l>
                  <l>(Where thou didſt never injure any one)</l>
                  <l>To ſee this place, and here in ſome few weeks</l>
                  <l>To do more miſchief then whole Generations</l>
                  <l>Can parallel?—Unfortunate <hi>Evadne!</hi>—</l>
                  <l>It had been better thou hadſt ever dwelt</l>
                  <l>In thoſe retirements, where ſmall ſins ſeem great,</l>
                  <l>And great Devotions ſmall, where folks make conſcience</l>
                  <l>To taſte of any thing that ever bled;</l>
                  <l>Then to be found there, where the blood of Queens</l>
                  <l>And Prieſts are ſacrifices to the Malice</l>
                  <l>Of wicked Men.—It this to be at Court?—</l>
                  <l>Ah poor, poor Girl! How hath thy Ignorance</l>
                  <l>Deluded thee?—And 'twas but juſt that ſhe</l>
                  <l>Who did begin to diſobey her father,</l>
                  <l>(Until he gave her new commands) ſhould be</l>
                  <l>Puniſh'd by that which tempted her. It is</l>
                  <l>Enough ſhe's innocent, although ſhe prove</l>
                  <l>Unfortunate. Whatever <hi>Neander</hi> did,</l>
                  <l>Heaven knows I never knew.—Yet I much doubt</l>
                  <l>I'm ſomewhat guilty, 'cauſe 'twas for my ſake.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Evadne.</stage>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter the Lords of the Councel, and ſeat themſelves. Enter a guard of Souldier with</hi> Neander, Geron, <hi>and</hi> Phroneſia, <hi>who are placed at the Bar, as Priſoners to receive ſentence. Enter Muſick; then the King leading his Queen crown'd, and in royal apparel; after them the Priest. They place themſelves on high in the middle of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:54200:38"/>and the Priest ſomewhat lower next the King. Then this Song is ſung.</hi>
               </stage>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus from the Priſon to the Throne</l>
                  <l>Vertue comes to claime her own:</l>
                  <l>And now appears</l>
                  <l>Upon that Throne a Star,</l>
                  <l>Who lately at the Bar</l>
                  <l>Stood only Jewel'd with her Tears.</l>
                  <l>1. Great Queen</l>
                  <l>2. Great Queen.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Chorus</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Whoever was ſo well content</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To ſuffer, and be innocent?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To ſuffer, and be innocent?</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <stage>Exit Muſick.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Gentleman leading Urania.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>The fair <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania!</hi> Madam, I muſt this day</l>
                  <stage>Turns to the Queen.</stage>
                  <l>Do honour to this Virgin.—And ſince it's</l>
                  <l>To noble natures a more pleaſing taske</l>
                  <l>To give rewards to Vertue, then puniſhments</l>
                  <l>To wicked folks; I'll in the firſt place ſhew</l>
                  <l>How lovely juſtice looks, when we are good;</l>
                  <l>And only ſin makes her ſeem terrible.—</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Urania,</hi> approach us.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gentlem.</speaker>
                  <l>Ah, great King!</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi>'s place (I doubt) will nearer be</l>
                  <l>The Bar then Throne—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>What mean'ſt thou?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gent.</speaker>
                  <l>See, O ſee</l>
                  <l>Thoſe cheeks that lately beauty wore, now pale</l>
                  <l>With guilt.—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Urania weeps.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Her crime.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gent.</speaker>
                  <l>She'th lately had a childe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>How know you this?—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gent.</speaker>
                  <l>By a ſtrange piece of chance:</l>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:54200:39"/>
                  <l>For being ſent in haſte by my Lord <hi>Pyrrhus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To bring herto you Majeſty; by chance,</l>
                  <l>I learnt of one o'th' ſervants of the Princeſs,</l>
                  <l>Near to what place he thought ſhe was: and when</l>
                  <l>I made enquiry there, at a ſmall houſe</l>
                  <l>I was acquinted at, the woman told me</l>
                  <l>She thought her I enquir'd for was i' th' houſe;</l>
                  <l>And asking of me many circumſtances,</l>
                  <l>She told me ſurely it muſt be the ſame:</l>
                  <l>Only (ſhe did in private add) ſhe took her</l>
                  <l>Not for a Virgin — (And as we thus diſcours'd,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Urania</hi> chanc'd to paſs before the door.)</l>
                  <l>A Virgin, ſaid I! It may be ſhe is married;</l>
                  <l>What, hath ſhe had a childe? ſhe told me; Yes,</l>
                  <l>(Though much in private) but 't was very much</l>
                  <l>Before her time; and ſhe affirms ſhe's married,</l>
                  <l>As did her mother, who this morning left her.</l>
                  <l>At this, I went in where I ſaw her enter:</l>
                  <l>And after ſome examinations, ſhe</l>
                  <l>Confeſt ſhe'd had a childe; but ſaid withall,</l>
                  <l>She had a husband too, and one who would</l>
                  <l>Dare own her for his wife: but would not tell me</l>
                  <l>His name or dwelling; and was very loath</l>
                  <l>To move a foot with me, but meerly by</l>
                  <l>Conſtraint as 'twere.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>And is this truth, <hi>Urania?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
                  <l>Speak to the King.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Urania.</speaker>
                  <l>It's true.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>And who's your Husband?—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2. <hi>Lord.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Be not aſham'd to name your Husband, Madam:</l>
                  <l>'T will be your ſhame if you name none.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Urania.</speaker>
                  <l>I'm not</l>
                  <l>Aſham'd to name him, but affraid.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>What is it?</l>
                  <l>Speak—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania.</speaker>
                  <l>I dare not diſobey, and by my Lord</l>
                  <l>I am authorized to name him when</l>
                  <l>My Honour ſhall be queſtion'd (who's more tender</l>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:54200:39"/>
                  <l>Of that then of his own)—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
                  <l>Name him.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Urania.</speaker>
                  <l>It is</l>
                  <l>The great <hi>Theander!</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                  <l>The Prince?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>What, are you marri'd</l>
                  <l>Unto the Prince <hi>Theander?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Kneels.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Urania.</speaker>
                  <l>O pardon me, great King,</l>
                  <l>That I refus'd not to be taken from</l>
                  <l>A Cottage to the boſom of a Prince,</l>
                  <l>On ſuch conditions as we dar'd to call</l>
                  <l>The Gods to witneſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Whether ſhe be his wife,</l>
                  <l>Or only dare's affirm it, though ſhe were</l>
                  <l>More to me then my hands or eyes, ſhe ſhould</l>
                  <l>Die ere I ſleep.—The Prince in ſome few houres</l>
                  <l>Will be in Town—If what ſhe ſays be falſe,</l>
                  <l>This news ſhall be his welcone.—But if true,</l>
                  <l>'Tis fit his coming be too late to ſave her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ran.</speaker>
                  <l>Ah great Prince!—Pity the diſtreſs'd, who hath</l>
                  <l>No friend to plead her cauſe—All I affirm</l>
                  <l>Is truth—<hi>Theander</hi> is my witneſs. See</l>
                  <stage>Takes a letter out of her boſom.</stage>
                  <l>That noble name.—This I receiv'd from him</l>
                  <l>Not three days ſince.—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>King reads it, and gives it the Queen</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis ſo. But know, <hi>Urania,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>My Crown will prove too heavie for your off-ſpring,</l>
                  <l>Nor may I mingle blood with thoſe ſmall folks</l>
                  <l>Who dwell in Cottages. Heaven, it ſeems,</l>
                  <l>Would not permit ſo foul a ſtain upon</l>
                  <l>My Family, but hath condemn'd to death</l>
                  <l>(What men in juſtice could not) that poor infant</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe only guilt was, that it muſt be born.—</l>
                  <l>No, know <hi>Unania,</hi> 'tis enough you have been</l>
                  <l>VVife to a Prince ſome months; you've liv'd enough</l>
                  <l>In that ſmall time: Now 'twill behove you to</l>
                  <l>Prepare for death; this day within three houres</l>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:54200:40"/>
                  <l>You are to looſe your head, 'cauſe 'tis not fit</l>
                  <l>To wear a Crown.—Marſhal, take her hence.</l>
                  <l>Let all things be prepar'd. I'll ſee her dead</l>
                  <l>By two this afternoon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ran.</speaker>
                  <l>Is there no mercy then?</l>
                  <l>Heaven help the friendleſs.—Such muſt never cry</l>
                  <l>To men for help, whoſe crime is poverty.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt Marſhal and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lords, had not this accident befallen me,</l>
                  <l>I'd been too bleſt. VViſe Heaven doth ſee't as fit</l>
                  <l>In all our joys to give us ſome allays,</l>
                  <l>As in our ſorrow comforts: when our Sails</l>
                  <l>Are fill'd with happieſt winds, then we moſt need</l>
                  <l>Some heavineſs to ballaſt us. Theſe are</l>
                  <l>The ways of Heaven, and we who are but earth</l>
                  <l>Muſt all ſubmit. I am afflicted for</l>
                  <l>The poor <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi> — But the Gods have ſure</l>
                  <l>(In death) rewards for thoſe who ſometimes fall</l>
                  <l>Nor for their crimes, but through a kind of ſad</l>
                  <l>Neceſſity.—I'm to proceed now to</l>
                  <l>A far more willing task, the ſentencing</l>
                  <l>Of thoſe moſt wicked perſons at the Bar.—</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Neander</hi> I condemn to looſe his head</l>
                  <l>Tomorrow morning, which I will have plac'd</l>
                  <l>Over his Lodgings, to ſhew, thoſe heads who dare</l>
                  <l>Contrive their Princes harm, do only meet</l>
                  <l>VVith ſuch advancement. <hi>Geron</hi> I adjudge</l>
                  <l>To die in Chayns, that bunger may devour</l>
                  <l>That little body malice yet hath left him.</l>
                  <l>(A proper Lent for ſuch a ſinner.) And</l>
                  <l>('Cauſe what <hi>Phroneſia</hi> did, ſhe did not know;</l>
                  <l>She ly'd, but did not know the conſequence,)</l>
                  <l>Her I condemn only to baniſhment.</l>
                  <l>And thus I hope to expiate the thoughts</l>
                  <l>I've had of my chaſte Queen, and holy Prieſt,</l>
                  <l>Through thoſe mens wickedneſs and teach the world,</l>
                  <l>That ſuch who dare be traytors to their King,</l>
                  <l>Do on themſelves the certain'ſt ruine, bring.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:54200:40"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                  <l>Heaven bleſs the King, and may our eyes ſtill ſee</l>
                  <l>Such Juſtice done on all that traytors be.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt Omnes.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Cleantha and her Nource.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleantha.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas, <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania!</hi> — Now thou haſt unriddl'd</l>
                  <l>How thou couldſt underſtand, and yet accept not</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Endymions</hi> Love.—Poor Heart, I pity thee.—</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Endymion</hi> now will be more baniſh'd, when</l>
                  <l>He hears <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>raaia</hi>'s dead.—Ah <hi>Urania,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVould thou hadſt a crime to die for, that</l>
                  <l>My juſt <hi>Endymion</hi> might leſs bewail thee.</l>
                  <l>VVhere can he now relieve himſelf? If Vertue</l>
                  <l>Be not ſecurity, who can be ſafe?—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nource.</speaker>
                  <l>VVhy Madam, here was now a marriage made</l>
                  <l>According to your Highneſs principles,</l>
                  <l>Purely for Love; without conſideration</l>
                  <l>Of Portion, or equality, or friends;</l>
                  <l>And here you ſee the end on't.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleanth.</speaker>
                  <l>Silly woman,</l>
                  <l>Talk not ſo Idly. —Had they underſtood</l>
                  <l>The force of Love, who thus condemn'd <hi>Urania,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>They ne'er had done it. And ſhall we diſeſteem</l>
                  <l>Religion, 'cauſe folks often ſuffer for't?</l>
                  <l>And think it is not true, becauſe 't hath Martyrs?</l>
                  <l>Wert thou not old, thou mightſt be brought to know</l>
                  <l>There is a Guſt in death when 'tis for love,</l>
                  <l>That's more then all that's taſte in all the world.</l>
                  <l>For the true meaſure of true love, is death;</l>
                  <l>And what falls ſhort of this, was never love:</l>
                  <l>And therefore when thoſe Tides do meet, and ſtrive,</l>
                  <l>And both ſwell high, but love is higheſt ſtill,</l>
                  <l>This is the trueſt ſatisfaction of</l>
                  <l>The perfectſt love: For here it ſees it ſelf</l>
                  <l>Indure the higheſt Teſt, and then it feels</l>
                  <l>The ſum of delectation, ſince it now</l>
                  <l>Attains its perfect end, and ſhews its object</l>
                  <l>By one intenſe Act, all it's Verity,</l>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:54200:41"/>
                  <l>VVhich by a thouſand, and ten thouſand words</l>
                  <l>It would have took a poor diluted pleaſure</l>
                  <l>To have imperfectly expreſt.—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Aſide.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nource.</speaker>
                  <l>Heaven bleſs me!</l>
                  <l>I do not wonder Lovers oft run Maz'd,</l>
                  <l>That think at this ſtrange rate. 'Twill crack my skull</l>
                  <l>To hear it longer. —Madam, will you not ſee</l>
                  <l>The execution?—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleant.</speaker>
                  <l>Not for ten thouſand VVorlds.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nource.</speaker>
                  <l>It is at hand.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleant.</speaker>
                  <l>Poor <hi>Urania!</hi> I</l>
                  <l>Can find no friends on earth to help thee; now</l>
                  <l>I will addreſs my ſelf to Heaven for thee,</l>
                  <l>VVho only can reprieve what Great-folks have</l>
                  <l>Condemn'd to Ruine, and 's the ſole defence</l>
                  <l>Through all the world, unto weak-innocence.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt Cleantha and Nource.</stage>
               <stage>
                  <hi>There appears a Scaffold covered with black, with many Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors about it. The King is preſent himſelf to ſee the Execution done before the Prince his arrival, which was at hand. Enter</hi> Urania <hi>in Black, weeping; led by two of the Princeſs's Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants in Black.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Poor heart! did I not fear the Prince's coming,</l>
                  <l>I would not ſee ſo ſad a ſpectacle.— / </l>
                  <l>But I'll retire a little.—I'd have her live</l>
                  <l>As long's ſhe may.—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Urania caſts her eyes on the Executioner.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sheriff.</speaker>
                  <l>Retire 'till you are call'd to do your office.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Executioner.</stage>
               <stage>The Two Gentlemen who attend her, conduct her to the Rayls of the Scaffold; where having wip'd her eyes. ſhe ſpeaks thus to the People.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ran.</speaker>
                  <l>—Did any thing but my own innocence</l>
                  <l>Lie now at ſtake (which now is all I've left</l>
                  <l>To comfort me) I ſhould not dare to ſpeak</l>
                  <l>Before ſo many Perſons. But, (though I</l>
                  <l>Muſt quire deſpair of Mercy in this world,</l>
                  <l>I hope I may find Charity, and that</l>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:54200:41"/>
                  <l>Good folks will credit a poor dying Perſon,</l>
                  <l>Although ſhe bring no witneſs but her vows.</l>
                  <l>All I am now condemn'd for, is my Birth.</l>
                  <l>That I was meanly born (which ſeems indeed</l>
                  <l>A Puniſhment; but not a Crime) (or if</l>
                  <l>It were, I could not help it ſure) for this</l>
                  <l>I'm doom'd to ſuffer, and my poverty</l>
                  <l>Muſt be reliev'd with death.—But though I can</l>
                  <l>Find no forgiveneſs in the world, I'm glad</l>
                  <l>I find it in my ſelf. I freely can</l>
                  <l>Forgive who e'er have injur<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d me, if any</l>
                  <l>Have done ſo (for I cannot tell) and this</l>
                  <l>Is ſome eaſe to me; though, perchance, the living</l>
                  <l>Do little heed the pardons of the dead.</l>
                  <l>I do not know I ever hurted any:</l>
                  <l>But if I have, I hope, they will forgive me.</l>
                  <l>Only my Lord <hi>Endymion</hi> I did once</l>
                  <l>Delude, to ſave my life (would Heaven I had not.)</l>
                  <l>But he is merciful to others, though</l>
                  <l>He'th met with little for himſelf.—I do</l>
                  <l>Confeſs, I'm marri'd to the Prince: But he,</l>
                  <l>He ſure will witneſs for me, 't was the Effect</l>
                  <l>Of his own choyce: I never did preſume</l>
                  <l>To think it, ere he told me 't ſhould be ſo.—</l>
                  <l>Since when, how faithful I have been unto him,</l>
                  <l>VVitneſs O'Heaven, and thoſe powers who know</l>
                  <l>The thoughts of every one; and only dare</l>
                  <l>To quit whom Kings condemn. And though I muſt</l>
                  <l>For this now ſuffer death, I cannot wiſh</l>
                  <l>It never had been ſo, becauſe it was</l>
                  <l>The Prince his pleaſure; whom to contradict,</l>
                  <l>VVere more then death to me.—And yet I feel</l>
                  <l>That death is bitter.— 'Tis an enemy</l>
                  <l>Looks cruelly on thoſe who have no friends</l>
                  <l>To ſpeak a little comfort to them.— 'Tis hard</l>
                  <l>To undergo the greateſt Task alone. —</l>
                  <l>But, 'tis my Fate, and Heaven muſt be obey'd;</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe ways, although they ſeem obſcure to men,</l>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:54200:42"/>
                  <l>Are known unto it ſelf, whole eyes increaſe</l>
                  <l>VVith it's own dark neſs ſtill. And't were not hard,</l>
                  <l>Now men have jud'd me thus unfit to live,</l>
                  <l>VVould Heaven aſſure me I am fit to die.—</l>
                  <l>'Tis a long Hazard that folks run in death:</l>
                  <l>And a ſhort warning rather doth diſturb</l>
                  <l>Then fit thoſe for it, whoſe poor judgments ne'er</l>
                  <l>Judge well, but when they doubt themſelves. Wer't not</l>
                  <l>For this, I could be well content, though young,</l>
                  <l>To find that Quiet in a Grave, I've miſt</l>
                  <l>Among the living, and cloſe up thoſe eyes</l>
                  <l>That have of late beheld ſo little pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>And that muſt ſee the brave <hi>Theander</hi> blam'd</l>
                  <l>For his unworthy choyce, his judgment queſtion'd,</l>
                  <l>VVhich were a living death, not to be bought</l>
                  <l>VVith all this world can give.—But I too long</l>
                  <l>Detain you with complaints, whoſe buſineſs is</l>
                  <l>To ſee me die.—Live happy, brave <hi>Theander!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>May all thy ſorrows die with thy <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And all thoſe joys live with thee, which ſhe took</l>
                  <l>In thy contents.—May'ſt thou be Happy in</l>
                  <l>A princeſs, Great, as thy own Merits, Bright</l>
                  <l>As thy own eyes, and Vertuous as</l>
                  <l>Are all thy Thoughts; and may ſhe honour thee</l>
                  <l>As truly as thy poor <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi> did.—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Executioner.</stage>
               <stage>She weeps.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Execut.</speaker>
                  <l>Are you ready, Madam?—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Uran.</speaker>
                  <l>VVho is this, Sir?—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gent.</speaker>
                  <l>—Madam.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ran.</speaker>
                  <l>VVho is it, Sir?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gent.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, It is your deſtiny.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Uran.</speaker>
                  <l>Is this he?—</l>
                  <l>Sir, can you inſtruct me what I am to do?</l>
                  <l>I never yet ſaw any body die.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gent.</speaker>
                  <l>You muſt kneel down.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ran.</speaker>
                  <l>How will he ſtrike?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gent.</speaker>
                  <l>VVith all the mercy that he can.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Execut.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, when</l>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:54200:42"/>
                  <l>You've ended all you have to ſay, be pleas'd</l>
                  <l>To kneel—Your face that way— And give ſome ſign</l>
                  <l>When I ſhall ſtrike—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ran.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray Sirs be near me</l>
                  <l>VVhen I do fall. I cannot tell what poſtures</l>
                  <l>Death may allow of.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gent.</speaker>
                  <l>You have our promiſe, Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ran.</speaker>
                  <l>And when I'm dead, pray Sirs, pray Sirs, permit</l>
                  <l>None but my Mother fit me for my Grave.</l>
                  <l>She will be careful of me; ſhe will pay</l>
                  <l>Holy Devotions for me, and bedew</l>
                  <l>With pious tears that Face ſhe ſtill hath lov'd.—</l>
                  <l>And may bleſt Heaven give comfort in her ſorrows;</l>
                  <l>And all thoſe Stars which have been hard to me,</l>
                  <l>Be merciful to her.—May my Misfortune</l>
                  <l>VVork on her only a more true content</l>
                  <l>In the low Sphere ſhe ſo ſecurely moves in.—</l>
                  <l>Bleſt Heaven aſſiſt me.—Sirs, farewell. Preſent</l>
                  <l>My humble Service to my noble Princeſs,</l>
                  <l>With thanks for all her favours in my Life,</l>
                  <l>And charity in death.—The gods reward</l>
                  <l>Your mercy, Gentlemen.—Bleſt Heaven aſſiſt me.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>She kneels, and the Executioner bares her neck.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Uran.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray— expect the ſign.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Execut.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhall.—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter in haſte Parthenia, Urania's Mother.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
                  <l>—Stay, ſtay the fatal blow.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>The King hearing the noyſe, comes forth.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>VVhat's this?—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
                  <l>A miſerable Mother come to ſave</l>
                  <l>Her only Childe.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Executioner, do your office.—Quick.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
                  <l>—Great King! —Dread Soveraign, hear,</l>
                  <l>Hear a diſtreſſed Mother.— Hear for their ſakes</l>
                  <l>That at your death muſt hear you.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>What will you ſay?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
                  <l>My Childe is innocent.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Do your office, Executioner.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
                  <l>O! ſtay, ſtay.—Great King, <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi> is</l>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:54200:43"/>
                  <l>A Princeſs born.—Her father was a King.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſay you?—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi>'s father was a King</l>
                  <l>Great, but unfortunate.—The King of <hi>Thrace.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>It is not poſſible.—The King of <hi>Thrace?</hi>—</l>
                  <l>And what are you?—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
                  <l>Great King, I'm now your Subject,</l>
                  <l>My name <hi>Parthenia,</hi> and my habitation</l>
                  <l>A little Cottage: But I once was known</l>
                  <l>By th' name of <hi>Cleopatra</hi> (great in Brith,</l>
                  <l>But greater in misfortune) and was wife</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Pyrocles</hi> the Vertuous Prince of <hi>Thrace;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of whom, all that remains, beſides his fame,</l>
                  <l>Is this poor childe, for whom I beg your mercy,</l>
                  <l>Not to extinguiſh with one ſtroke all that</l>
                  <l>The ſtrokes of Fate have left among the ruines</l>
                  <l>Of a late glorious Family.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Her language.</l>
                  <l>Beſpeaks her ſomething elſe then her mean habit.</l>
                  <l>'Tis ſtrange.—But, how do you make good</l>
                  <l>What you affirm? — How came you to <hi>Arcadia?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
                  <l>Will you Majeſty be pleas'd in ſhort</l>
                  <l>To hear my ſtory?—I ſhall be brief.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Say on.</l>
                  <l>But if you ſpeak not truth, you ſhall partake</l>
                  <l>Your daughters Fate.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
                  <l>Let heaven by my witneſs;</l>
                  <l>And if I lye, my Executioner.</l>
                  <l>I ſhall not now repeat the long misfortunes</l>
                  <l>Of my unhappy Prince, by that dire War,</l>
                  <l>His Rebel-Subjects rais'd againſt him, through</l>
                  <l>His too great goodneſs. Theſe reports enough</l>
                  <l>Already have afflicted all good ears,</l>
                  <l>And all good hearts.—I now ſhall only tell you,</l>
                  <l>When he had acted out his Tragedy,</l>
                  <l>And wicked hands had made him glorious</l>
                  <l>By patient ſuffering all that Malice could</l>
                  <l>Inflict upon his perſon. They next come</l>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:54200:43"/>
                  <l>To his Relations. How they did betray,</l>
                  <l>And butcher divers of them, all have heard,</l>
                  <l>And I have felt.—I having now remaining</l>
                  <l>Of all my Treaſure, this poor Jewel only</l>
                  <l>Some few Months old; and knowing how ſoon Kingdoms</l>
                  <l>Seem to grow weary of th' unfortunate,</l>
                  <l>Reſolv'd (when all look'd ſtrange upon me) to</l>
                  <l>Retire to ſome ſmall place, ſuch as my fortune</l>
                  <l>Could make my own, and there to buy my Peace</l>
                  <l>With my obſcurity, and learn to be</l>
                  <l>Contented with a little, ſince Heaven thought</l>
                  <l>Much too much for me. Hither then I came,</l>
                  <l>Invited by the Peace of this bleſt Region,</l>
                  <l>And purchas'd the ſmall Cottage where I dwell,</l>
                  <l>And learn'd to change my Scepter for a ſheep-hook</l>
                  <l>And thus I bred this childe, and never told her</l>
                  <l>Ought of her Father's or of my Misfortunes,</l>
                  <l>Not willing to diſturb thoſe ſweet contents</l>
                  <l>She took in being all ſhe hop'd to be,</l>
                  <l>And all ſhe underſtood: ſhe felt no care,</l>
                  <l>And with more pleaſure govern'd her ſmall flock,</l>
                  <l>Then her unhappy Father his great Kingdom.</l>
                  <l>And this was my content, and Heaven can witneſs</l>
                  <l>How oft I've bleſt thoſe Powers it doth contain</l>
                  <l>For this condition, and how little I</l>
                  <l>Have envi'd any one. But Heaven that oft</l>
                  <l>Affronts the higheſt Probabilities,</l>
                  <l>And gratifies by ways were never thought of;</l>
                  <l>T'incourage men to pray, but not preſcribe:</l>
                  <l>When all my greatneſs now was ſet; when I</l>
                  <l>Had loſt the Twi-light too of hope, and was</l>
                  <l>Gone far from all my Loſſes to forget them:</l>
                  <l>When my great Palace, where I once commanded,</l>
                  <l>Was ſhrunk into a Cottage to obey in;</l>
                  <l>When I deſpair'd to ſee <hi>Urania</hi> great,</l>
                  <l>(The only ſpark that ſtill kept in my Life)</l>
                  <l>And only pray'd ſhe might be innocent:</l>
                  <l>In this low Ebb, when all my hopes were grown</l>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:54200:44"/>
                  <l>More proſtrate then my fortune, Heaven begins</l>
                  <l>To dawn upon me, and inſtruct me, thoſe</l>
                  <l>Are neerer it who kneel in humble Cells,</l>
                  <l>Then ſuch as ſtand on tip toe on high Towrs.</l>
                  <l>For now <hi>Theander</hi> makes <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi> more</l>
                  <l>A Princeſs then a Kingdom could, by courting</l>
                  <l>Her as a ſhepherdeſs; and ſhews the world,</l>
                  <l>That more then Chance conduced to her greatneſs.</l>
                  <l>Immerit perſons may be born thus, but</l>
                  <l>By wiſe folks, they will ne'er be choſen to it.</l>
                  <l>And ſuch <hi>Theander</hi>'s known to all the world.</l>
                  <l>I could have told <hi>Theander</hi> the whole truth</l>
                  <l>When he would needs aske my conſent to wed</l>
                  <l>My erſt neglected childe, but that I would not</l>
                  <l>Leſſen thoſe great contents he ſeem'd to take</l>
                  <l>In his <hi>Arcadia,</hi> that a Cottage had</l>
                  <l>Brought forth a perſon fit to be a Princeſs.</l>
                  <l>But chiefly I reflected on the dark</l>
                  <l>Meandrous paths of fate, and gratifi'd</l>
                  <l>My former ſufferance, by being now admitted</l>
                  <l>Into its Councels, and the Proſpect of</l>
                  <l>Its hidden ſteps: 'Till now, it thinks not fit,</l>
                  <l>I longer ſhould enjoy the priviledge</l>
                  <l>It hath deny'd the more deſerving world.</l>
                  <l>For witneſs of all this, I do invoke</l>
                  <l>Thoſe powers who never teſtifie untruths,</l>
                  <l>And here produce thoſe ſmall remains of Greatneſs</l>
                  <stage>She ſhews ſeveral very rich Jewels.</stage>
                  <l>Misfortune yet hath left me. See here, great Prince</l>
                  <l>That ſo fam'd Jewel, which ſo many Kings</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Thrace</hi> have worn, and with ſuch veneration</l>
                  <l>Have ſtill preſer'd, on an old Prophecie,</l>
                  <l>This ſhould preſerve the <hi>Thracian</hi> Family.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>I need no Teſtimony but thoſe words</l>
                  <l>All Queens might bluſh to hear from Cottagers.</l>
                  <l>But is it poſſible ſo mean a place</l>
                  <l>So long ſhould hold great <hi>Cleopatra?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>How could ſhe lift her eyes to Heaven, beneath</l>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:54200:44"/>
                  <l>So low a roofe? When they look'd up for mercy,</l>
                  <l>How were they minded of it's Cruelty?</l>
                  <l>Unheard of Patience!—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleopat.</speaker>
                  <l>Know, great Prince, and know it</l>
                  <l>From one who hath experimented greatneſs too;</l>
                  <l>When I had ſatisfi'd my ſelf, in my</l>
                  <l>Endeavours of regaining my loſt Rights,</l>
                  <l>And ſaw it all unproſperous (as if</l>
                  <l>Heaven long enough had giv'n one Family</l>
                  <l>The priviledge to govern other folks)</l>
                  <l>I was as well content to be the firſt</l>
                  <l>Muſt learn to act again with common people,</l>
                  <l>As he who firſt was call'd from them to rule;</l>
                  <l>And did endeavour by my Vertue to</l>
                  <l>Deſerve again what (poſſibly) my ſin</l>
                  <l>Had made me looſe. And thus I found in patience,</l>
                  <l>As much content in ſuffering, as I did</l>
                  <l>In Moderation in proſperity.</l>
                  <l>And pay'd to Heaven, as true, as real thanks</l>
                  <l>For this, as e'er I did for that.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Great Queen,</l>
                  <l>The Prophecy is now fulfill'd: That Jewel</l>
                  <l>Will ſerve to ſatisfie the world as much</l>
                  <l>Of all you ſay, as your own words have me:</l>
                  <l>And thus preſerve the <hi>Thracian</hi> Family.—</l>
                  <stage>Embraceth and kiſſeth <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania.</stage>
                  <l>Dear Daughter.—Still be happy—And forgive</l>
                  <l>Our ignorance.— I cannot love thee better,</l>
                  <l>Then at that very time I did condemn thee;</l>
                  <l>I could as well have ſentenc'd my two eyes.</l>
                  <stage>Salutes Cleopatra.</stage>
                  <l>And pardon us, dear ſiſter, if we firſt</l>
                  <l>Ask'd pardon where we did moſt need it.—Call</l>
                  <l>Our Queen immediatley, and tell <hi>Cleantha,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Urania</hi> is alive.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pyrrh.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhall be proud</l>
                  <l>To be the Meſſenger.—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Pyrrh.</stage>
               <stage>Trumpets without.</stage>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:54200:45"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>What's that?—The Prince is come. —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
                  <l>The Prince is come.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King</speaker>
                  <l>What will <hi>Theander</hi> ſay, to ſee his dear</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Urania</hi> thus attir'd at his return?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ran.</hi> He'll ſay you're merciful.—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Queen and Cleantha.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>My Queen! See here great <hi>Cleopatra,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And call her Siſter.— Take <hi>Cleantha,</hi> take</l>
                  <l>Her thou haſt wept for—<hi>Pyrrhus</hi> hath told you</l>
                  <l>All Heavens goodneſs.—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>The Queen Salutes</hi> Cleopatra, <hi>then runs and embraceth Urania. Enter</hi> Theander.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>See here the Prince.—My Son.—</l>
                  <l>Never more welcome.—Never did more joy</l>
                  <l>Spring from more ſorrow.—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>He ſixeth his eyes on Uran.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theand.</speaker>
                  <l>—Bleſs me, dread Sir!</l>
                  <l>What ſcene doth entertain me?—Are your joys</l>
                  <l>Expreſs'd by ſacrifice?—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Theander,</hi> take,</l>
                  <l>Take thy <hi>Urania,</hi> and wonder not</l>
                  <l>At any thing but her.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theand.</speaker>
                  <l>My Triumphs more</l>
                  <l>Affright me then my conqueſts.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                  <l>My Son, be happy</l>
                  <l>In thy beſt choyce.—Let not thy wonder make</l>
                  <l>Us longer languiſh.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theand.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, I will believe,</l>
                  <stage>Salutes the Queen.</stage>
                  <l>And hope in time to underſtand— Dear Cozen.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Goes to ſalute Cleantha, who ſteps back<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleanth.</speaker>
                  <l>—Sir, when you firſt have done</l>
                  <l>Your merited reſpects unto the Queen</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Thrace,</hi> your Mother; then to your <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I ſhall be thankful for the honour you</l>
                  <l>Too early do vouchſafe me.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theand.</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt obey</l>
                  <l>What Heaven knows when I ſhall underſtand.</l>
                  <stage>Salutes Cleopatra.</stage>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:54200:45"/>
                  <l>This is an earlier tribute then I thought</l>
                  <stage>Embraceth Urania, who cries on him.</stage>
                  <l>To pay yourlips.—My dear <hi>Urania,</hi> why</l>
                  <l>Doſt thou conſpire to my diſtraction?— Why</l>
                  <l>This Black? —And why theſe tears?—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Heaven bleſs you both;</l>
                  <l>And may your Loves encreaſe ſtill with your days:</l>
                  <l>May you be freſh as ſpring, as Autumn fruitful,</l>
                  <l>And know no Winter of adverſity:</l>
                  <l>And Heaven that hath done wonders in your Loves,</l>
                  <l>May it do wonders in th' effects of it.—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>They both bow to the King, and then ſtep a little aſide and talk together. Enter Prieſt.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Priest.</speaker>
                  <l>A day full of wonders.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Aday</l>
                  <l>All miracle.—How merciful is Heaven</l>
                  <l>To thoſe it loves?—Who would be ever Bad,</l>
                  <l>When Vertuous folks are thus rewarded in</l>
                  <l>The midſt of their diſtreſs?—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>The Prince returns to the company again.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theand.</speaker>
                  <l>Cozen—</l>
                  <stage>Salutes the Princeſs.</stage>
                  <l>Your pardon.— Happy is this meeting.</l>
                  <l>I am oblig'd for all the joy I ſee</l>
                  <stage>Bows to the company.</stage>
                  <l>Start out of ſorrow now at my return.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleant.</speaker>
                  <l>Heaven give you joy of your <hi>Urania.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theand.</speaker>
                  <l>You have oblig'd me Madam, that you have</l>
                  <l>Dealt ſtill ſo gently with your ſervant.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleant.</speaker>
                  <l>She ne'er</l>
                  <l>Had been eſteemed ſo, had you eſteem'd</l>
                  <l>Me worthy of your Councel, Sir; but now</l>
                  <l>I ſhall indeavour to repay her all</l>
                  <l>Thoſe ſervices I have receiv'd from her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theand.</speaker>
                  <l>She's ſtill your ſervant, Cozen.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleant. Aſide.</speaker>
                  <l>How can there be ſuch mirth; when brave</l>
                  <l>Lives ſadly in an unjuſt baniſhment?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Endymion</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theand.</speaker>
                  <l>I long to eaſe my wonder, and to know</l>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:54200:46"/>
                  <l>The ſtory of great <hi>Cleopatra;</hi> how</l>
                  <l>She'th been ſo long obſcur'd to all the world,</l>
                  <l>But, to her ſelf.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>We'll find a ſcene for that,</l>
                  <l>Leſs like the face of ſorrow, 'Tis enough</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Urania</hi> is a Princeſs, and had Fortune</l>
                  <l>In ought but in her blindneſs been like juſtice,</l>
                  <l>Had worn the Crown of <hi>Thrace.</hi>—Only my Daughter,</l>
                  <l>My dear <hi>Urania,</hi> ask me on this place,</l>
                  <l>I ſo have injur'd thee, what I ſhall do</l>
                  <l>To expiate my ignorance of thy worth.</l>
                  <l>Ask what thou wilt, I ſhall not find a tongue</l>
                  <l>To give thee a denyal.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ran.</speaker>
                  <l>Great Prince, I do not</l>
                  <l>Want a requeſt, had I but merit to</l>
                  <l>Deſerve it firſt, then confidence to ask it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Ask it; or you chuſe the perfect'ſt way</l>
                  <l>To diſoblige me.— What is it?—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Uran.</speaker>
                  <l>It is</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Endymions</hi> Liberty.—'Twas by his goodneſs,</l>
                  <l>I liv'd to ſee this day, whoſe only Cloud</l>
                  <l>Is his confinement. —Pardon the boldneſs Sir</l>
                  <l>You're pleas'd to give me; and the gratitude</l>
                  <l>I hope the Gods will never take from me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>You have my word, do with it what you pleaſe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Endymion</hi> ſhall have his liberty.—</l>
                  <l>I ſhall give order for it.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theand.</speaker>
                  <l>Your pardon Sir,</l>
                  <l>If your commands already are obey'd.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Endymion</hi> is return'd.—I met him ere</l>
                  <l>He was imbarq'd, and having been inform'd,</l>
                  <l>From my <hi>Urania,</hi> all his cares for her,</l>
                  <l>I ſtay'd him, hoping from your goodneſs to</l>
                  <l>Obtain his pardon.— For the love <hi>Cleantha</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So truly bears him, I have no more to ſay</l>
                  <l>Againſt it, then againſt my own I bare</l>
                  <l>To my <hi>Urania,</hi> when I thought her leſs.</l>
                  <l>And ſince the Gods have made her great for me,</l>
                  <l>'Twill be but gratitude in me to do</l>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:54200:46"/>
                  <l>Some of their buſineſs for them, and reward</l>
                  <l>So brave a Vertue as <hi>Endymion</hi> owns,</l>
                  <l>And make him great for his <hi>Cleantha</hi> too.</l>
                  <l>Eſpecially, ſince by their goodneſs, I</l>
                  <l>Have power to do it.—The war in <hi>Theſſaly</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Hath found a happy end.—And there I've left</l>
                  <l>Thoſe hands which made that Scepter ſtoop, who now</l>
                  <l>Want but a ſcoene to do new wonders in.</l>
                  <l>And this may prove rebellious <hi>Thrace,</hi> if you</l>
                  <l>(Dread Sir) approve it fit I wear that Crown</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi> gives me. In this expedition,</l>
                  <l>And in this conqueſt too, the brave <hi>Endymion</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall be my ſecond.— What ſhall I not expect from</l>
                  <l>Such Vertue and ſuch Valour when they meet?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>I have of late receiv'd ſuch mercies, that</l>
                  <l>I cannot think of any thing which looks</l>
                  <l>Like cruelty.— And in my condemnations,</l>
                  <l>Heaven hath done miracles, to keep me from</l>
                  <l>Horrid injuſtice. Therefore wonder not,</l>
                  <l>All that you ask is ſo ſoon granted you.—</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cleantha,</hi> take then thy <hi>Endymion,</hi> be</l>
                  <l>More bleſt in him then greatneſs e'er could make thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Cleantha bows.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                  <l>And now you're doing works of mercy Sir,</l>
                  <l>Hear one intreaty more, (not for their ſakes</l>
                  <l>For whom I ask, but for this days ſake, which</l>
                  <l>Hath been a day of mercy to us all.)</l>
                  <l>Let not <hi>Neander,</hi> nor old <hi>Geron</hi> die.</l>
                  <l>A baniſhment for life, will more prepare</l>
                  <l>Them for their deaths; and thus your mercy ſhall</l>
                  <l>Beſt fit them for the mercy of the Gods.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>What you propoſe, hath much of piety</l>
                  <l>And mercy too (the works of this day) and</l>
                  <l>Mayn't be deni'd.— And now I've one requeſt</l>
                  <l>To you my honour'd Prieſt (becauſe I'd give</l>
                  <l>Joy to all honeſt hearts this day) your leave,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> (my beſt confident) may ſerve</l>
                  <l>The fair <hi>Evadne.</hi>—</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:54200:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prieſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Great Prince, I am oblig'd,</l>
                  <l>My poor <hi>Evadne</hi> is ſo much your care:</l>
                  <l>It ſhall be mine, ſhe ſtill ſhall think that beſt</l>
                  <l>Your majeſty is pleas'd to chuſe for her.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Endymion.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theand.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Endymion!</hi> Why ſo ſlowly to thy joys?</l>
                  <l>Reap here the fruits of gratitude and mercy,</l>
                  <l>And ſee thoſe Stars again thou doſt adore.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Takes him by the hand, and leads him to</hi> Cleantha, <hi>who kneels down and kiſſeth her hand.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cleant.</speaker>
                  <l>VVelcome, my Lord.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, you're welcome from your baniſhment.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>You've only now this Ladies leave to ask</l>
                  <l>For any thing you'd have—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Endym.</speaker>
                  <l>I'm happy in</l>
                  <l>Your royal mercy Sir, and hope in time.</l>
                  <l>To be ſo too in hers.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>You need not fear</l>
                  <l>Your ſentence, when <hi>Cleantha</hi> is your judge.—</l>
                  <l>But let us all away, and ſatisfie—</l>
                  <l>Our ſelves with what we've ſo long travell'd with;</l>
                  <l>And let the world learn from this ſtory, though</l>
                  <l>Heaven may a while correct the Vertuous,</l>
                  <l>Yet will it wipe their eyes again, and make</l>
                  <l>Their Faces whiter with their tears. Innocence</l>
                  <l>Conceal'd is the ſtolen-pleaſure of the Gods,</l>
                  <l>VVhich never ends in ſhame, as that of men</l>
                  <l>Doth oft-times do; but like the Sun breaks forth,</l>
                  <l>VVhen it hath gratifi'd another world,</l>
                  <l>And to our unexpecting eyes appears</l>
                  <l>More Glorious through it's late obſcurity.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prieſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Unvertuous folks a while may find ſome Reſt;</l>
                  <l>But in the end, the good are only bleſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt Omn.</stage>
               <pb facs="tcp:54200:47"/>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
